<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A heavenly conference for Sions saints, to enlighten themselves, and teach their children. Together, with the saints beliefe. / By Iohn Turner, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, in Gardiners Lane, Westminster.</title>
            <author>Turner, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1171_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867740</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867740</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120063</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120063)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1171[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A heavenly conference for Sions saints, to enlighten themselves, and teach their children. Together, with the saints beliefe. / By Iohn Turner, a prisoner of Jesus Christ, in Gardiners Lane, Westminster.</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 11th."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Heavenly Conference for <hi>Sions</hi> SAINTS, To enlighten themſelves, and teach their Children. Together, With the SAINTS Beliefe. By <hi>Iohn Turner,</hi> a priſoner of Jeſus Chriſt, in <hi>Gardiners</hi> Lane, <hi>Westminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mal. 3. 16. 17.</bibl> 
               <hi>Then ſpake they that feared the Lord, every one to his neighbour, and the Lord hearkned and heard it, and a booke of remembrance was written before him for them that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Lord, and that thought upon his name. And they ſhall be to me, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, in that day that I ſhall doe this, for a flocke, and I will ſpare them, as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerveth him.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Deut. 6. 6. 7. </bibl>
               <hi>And theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhalbe in thine heart. And thou ſhalt rehearſe them continually unto thy children, and ſhalt talke of them when thou tarieſt in thine houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lieſt downe, and when thou riſeſt up.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luk. 2. 46, 47. </bibl>
               <hi>And it came to paſſe three dayes after, that they found him in the Temple, ſitting in the midſt of the doctors, both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, and asking them queſtions. And all that heard him, were aſtonied at his underſtanding and anſwers.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:2"/>
            <head>Psal. 16. 3. Moſt excellent SAINTS of SION.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r onely Lord hath taught, that Light is come into the world, and men loved darkeneſſe rather then light, becauſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> 
               <hi>their deeds were evill, whereby the Book of God hath beene ſealed with ſeven ſeales, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 5. 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 9.</note> 
               <hi>none could looke into the truth thereof, which hath cauſed people to leave the foundation of true faith (the written word) and beleeve as the Church and Prieſts beleeve. But the lyon of the tribe of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>of the root of</hi> David, <hi>hath opened the ſame, to the terrour of his enemies, and comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of his beloved Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And becauſe they could not prevaile to hide all</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6. 14.</note> truth, they rouled <hi>up as a ſcroule Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power, and Church-Government (denying</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 9. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>him to raigne over them) which hath cauſed Chriſts word to be contemned, as inſufficient for prudency in performing Divine Ordinances, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim, 3, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>thereby have cauſed the people to follow that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which the Prieſts doe appoynt them, changing the manner of worſhip, as gallants</hi> change <note place="margin">2 Pet. 5. 15. Prov. 24, 21.</note> their faſhions, ever now and then in a new ſhape.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And leſt their evill ſhould be eſpied, they have cauſed 4 Angels to hold the 4 winds of Chriſts</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Church, power &amp; government, that they ſhould not blow upon the Earth, Sea, or any Trees, by which Locuſts doe riſe out of the ſmoake of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 9. 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>pit, and with the fire, ſmoake, and brimſtone, which hath proceeded out of their mouthes, they have darkened the third part of the Sun-light of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 8. 12, &amp; 9, 18.</note> 
               <hi>the Goſpel, the third part of the inferior moon-light of the Law, and the third part of the truth of Chriſts miniſtry, and thereby cauſed the powers of the Earth to reele to and fro like a Drunkard, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay 24. 20. Rev. 6. 16. 17.</note> 
               <hi>quake, and ſay, alas, alas we know not what to do; hide us from the preſence of the Lamb, for his wrath (in his regall power and Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come) and we cannot ſtand, for he will condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (without reſpect of perſons) all evil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Government and Governours, Worſhip and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers; and then you ſhall be ſo borne up on every ſide with earthen props, that men ſhall not dare ſpeake againſt this Beaſt, neither teach Jeſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt to be the Saviour of the world (what gifts ſoever God indu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them with) without a licenſe from theſe evill angels, or Patentees of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the good Angel (notwithſtanding theſe) hath ſealed the Servants of God in the fore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> lead,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 7, 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>authorizing them to teach all his truths among all his people in all earthly dominions, by vertue</hi> Only <note place="margin">Marke 16. 15.</note> 
               <hi>of his power, and requires them ſo to doe, upon
<pb facs="tcp:120063:3"/> paine of his diſpleaſure: by whoſe authority I here</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act, 4. 19:</note> 
               <hi>imploy my meane talent, (without their licenſe) knowing, that it is better to obey God them man, and to ſet forth the whole truth of God revealed unto me that I may be guiltleſſe of the</hi> bloud of <note place="margin">Act. 20, 26, 27</note> all men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And having obtained this honour of the Lord once againe, to be a priſoner for maintaining his truth (this being the ſeventh time of my impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and fifteenth yeare, no cauſe having ever being ſhewed) cannot chuſe but ſpeak by writing, I (being ſet of the Lord apart thereunto, and taken</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act, 4, 20. 2 Theſſ. 1. 8.</note> 
               <hi>off from all other imployments) that ignorance (whereof God will be revenged in flames of fire) may be expelled; Faith, ſtedfaſtneſſe, and true worſhip embraced: theſe evill angels (by the word of Chriſts mouth) prevented in their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 9. 6. Exod. 10. 19. Rev. 18. 21.</note> 
               <hi>hiding the truth; and the Locuſts (that with their heads and tailes make men weary of their lives) by the Weſt-wind of Gods favour blowne into the Sea, appoynted for their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved, it is for the unfolding of Gods truth, and thy good, that I have penned the ſame, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the example of the Lamb, who diſcovered the Phariſees iniquitie, and unfolded the truth, by</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 2, 46, 47.</note> 
               <hi>queſtioning with them, and anſwering them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whoſe practice is my preſident: And though the Pen-man were not a Prophet, (as many call Prophets) neither the ſonne of a Prophet; yet I</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos. 7. 14.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:120063:4"/> 
               <hi>pray thee, in the feare of God, read it careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, try it diligenly, judge unpartially, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it lovingly, and refuſe not what thou ſeeſt appeare to bee truths herein, but yeeld conſcion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to practice the ſame, and teach it unto thy children faithfully, with all diligence; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that God, for the good of his, will bring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 4, 6. 1 Cor. 1, 27, 28 29.</note> 
               <hi>light out of darkeneſſe, making fooliſh things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found wiſe, and weake ſtrong, and hath choſen baſe things, and things that are not, to bring to</hi> nought things that are, <hi>leſt men ſhould rejoyce in their</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery humane learning, as in theſe <note place="margin">Rev. 16. 17.</note> dayes too much they doe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I humbly beſeech you, in the feare of God,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jam 21. Heb. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. Heb. 10. 37. 38.</note> 
               <hi>have not the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in reſpect of perſons, neither feare perſecution for well doing; looke not backe, preferring worldly friends before Chriſts truth, God will be a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Marke 10. 19.</note> 
               <hi>friend unto thee, then all thou canſt loſe for his ſake, giving thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n hundred fold recompence in this life, and in the world to come life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:4"/>
            <head>The Table of the Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MAns eſtate before his fall. <hi>Page</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>Mans eſtate in his fall, with the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. 4.</item>
               <item>Mans eſtate ſince his fall, and how wee ſhall know the Scriptures to be Gods word. 16.</item>
               <item>What every one ought to doe, ſince his fall in his perſonall eſtate. 26.</item>
               <item>What in his houſe, among his children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with the civill Magiſtrates duty, in matters of worſhip. 27.</item>
               <item>What a true Church of Chriſt is, how it comes to be a Church, and by what markes it is to be knowne. 29.</item>
               <item>What parts of Chriſts Church are eſſentiall and what ornamentall. 32.</item>
               <item>What Bookes the Church of Chriſt ought to read and obey. 34.</item>
               <item>What Officers belong to every Church of Chriſt, and who ought to make and ordaine them. 35.</item>
               <item>What the peoples dutie is to the Miniſter, and what maintenance he ought to have. 36.</item>
               <item>What the Miniſter muſt do for the people, with what dutie other Officers ought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. 36.</item>
               <item>How the poore ought to be relieved. 38.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:120063:5"/>
               <item>What Baptiſme and the Lords Supper ſeale un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. 39.</item>
               <item>The neceſſitie of being a member of a true Church, the end why, with the benefit thereof. 44.</item>
               <item>What one muſt doe to be a member. 46.</item>
               <item>How one brother muſt behave himſelf towards another brother, being members. 49.</item>
               <item>What a falſe Church is, how a falſe Church is to be known, and what cauſes it ſo to be. 49.</item>
               <item>Who are falſe Miniſters or Prophets. 54.</item>
               <item>Whether one may ſtand a member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> pray with their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or heare any of them preach. 55.</item>
               <item>What Church all Gods people were converted in. 56.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15. Jer. 2. 7, 1 Tim, 1. 19.</note> A created facultie of the ſoule, witneſſing truth on Gods part, by the thoughts accuſing or excuſing one another, and cannot be drawn to any partialitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved the Printer having failed in this queſtion, and theſe in this Errata, I pray except them here, and as you find them mend them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 1. <hi>l. 8. Ro.</hi> 4. 7 for 4. 17. p. 5. <hi>l. 29. r. terrified,</hi> for terrible p 7. <hi>l. 18. Mat.</hi> 9. 10. for 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 12. <hi>l. 1. Rev.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 5. for 21, 5, p. 22. <hi>l 25, 1 Kin.</hi> 22 for 21: p. 23. <hi>l. 5. Deut.</hi> 5. 30. for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 32 p. 21 r. <hi>propheſies</hi> for promiſes. <hi>Iſay</hi> 5. for 50. p. 26. <hi>l. 2. 1 Cor.</hi> 16. 12. for 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. 27. <hi>l</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. r <hi>ſame</hi> for Saints. p. 30. <hi>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor.</hi> 15. 3 for 5. 3. p. 13. <hi>l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ro.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for 1. 7. p. 34. <hi>l 10 Ioel</hi> 2. 21. for 2. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <hi>l.</hi> 28. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, for 1200. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>l. 14. r. higher Powers, Father, Mother, King Master, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120063:5"/>
            <head>A Heavenly Conference, for <hi>Sions Saints.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Queſtion. <hi>HOw comes Man and all Creatures to have being?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God Almighty created and made <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 1. Col. 1. 16. Revel. 14. 7 Pſal. 146. 6.</note> them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Of what did God make Man and all Creatures?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 1. Iſa. 45. 9. Rom. 4. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of that he had created. For to Create is to call forth of nothing, that is not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what means did God create althings:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 1. 3. 10. Heb. 11. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Only by his Word.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is God, who is ſo powerfull to make all things by his Word?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18. Acts 3 14. 1 Pet 1. 11. Ioh, 6. 68. 1 Ioh 5. 10. Ioh. 4. 24 &amp; 1. 3 Iſa. 9. 6 Revel. 4. 11. Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8. Pro. 16. 4. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. Gen. 1. 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is an Almighty, Holy, Eternall Spirit, not only the Maker, but governour of all things.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore did God create and make man and all things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For his pleaſure, &amp; to ſerve &amp; obey him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what likeneſſe did God make man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In his owne Image.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what was man created the Image of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:120063:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In Soveraignty and perpetuity. <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 6. Gen. 9. 2, 3. Math. 25. 46. Dan. 12. 2. Iohn 5. 29. Gen. 1. 31. Mark 7. 37. Tit. 1. 2. Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 31. Mar. 7. 37.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what eſtate did God create and make man and beaſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In an abſolute perfect eſtate without any defect, for the perfect God could not make any thing unperfectly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>From whence did the Fiſhes, Beaſts and Birds receive their ſoules?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the earth and waters, from whence <note place="margin">Gen, 1. 20. 22. 24. Eccl. 3. 21. 12. 7. Rev. 16. 3.</note> they received their bodies.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whither ſhall the ſoule of the fiſhes, beaſts and birds return when it diſſolves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To the earth and waters from whence <note place="margin">Pſal. 104. 29. Eccl. 12. 7. &amp; 3. 12. Revel. 16. 3. Pſal. 104 29.</note> they came: If it were not ſo, they ſhould goe to heaven as well as mens.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When dyes the ſoules of the fiſhes, beasts and birds?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Their ſoules and bodies dye together.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>From whence did man receive his body?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 4. Levit. 17. 14. Gen. 3. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the earth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whither ſhal mans body go when it diſſolves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To the earth from whence it came.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Shall mans body continue in the earth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iob 19. 25, 26, 27. 1 Cor. 15. 12 23. 1 Theſ. 4. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>for ever?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, it ſhall riſe againe at the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>From whence did man receive his ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From the breath of the Almighty. <note place="margin">Geneſis 2. 7. 1 Cor. 15. 43. Math. 10. 28. 1 Cor. 15. 45. Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 7. Ma. th. 25. 31, 36.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:120063:6"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is mans ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An everlaſting ſpirituall ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the difference between the body</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lu. 23. 43. 1 Cor. 15 51. Iſay 40. 6, 7, 8. Mat. 25. 31, 46.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſoule of man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The body is mortall and ſubject to dye, and the ſoule is immortall and can never dye.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whither ſhall the ſoule of man goe when it parteth from the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To heaven or hell at the departure. <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7, 8. Lu. 33. 34. Math. 25. 46. 1 Cor. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth the ſoule of man dye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, it ever liveth in pleaſure or paine.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whereunto was man created and made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To be Lord of the Earth and all therein. <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 3, 3. Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 8, 5, 6, 7, 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did man fall in his created eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; he neither did nor could in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 19, 20, &amp; 1. 31. Tit. 1. 2.</note> creation, for perfection cannot faile.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What did the Lord for man after he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee gave him Heaven with a covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 15, 16, 17. Heb. 8. 6, 7 Ro. 10. 5. Levi. 18. 5. Gal. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> condition of worke which hee would have performed: For the man that doth the worke lives in the worke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did man condiſcend unto this Covenant which God made with him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee went about the covenanted worke, <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 2, 3. &amp; 17. 10. 23. Math. 21. 28, 29, 30, 31.</note> which proves agreement.</p>
            <p>For if one ſpeake and the other goes about the worke, it proves conſent.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did not the Lord force man to this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:120063:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By no other meanes then ſetting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 9. 16. 17. Eſay 2. 3. Pſal. 110. 3. 2 Cor. 9. 13. Gen. 2. 15, 17.</note> before him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was the condition God made with man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That he ſhould doe what God required, and forbeare the tree of knowledge of good and evil.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know we our created duty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the true underſtanding of nature. <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 14, 15,</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was the reward, if man had kept Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The enjoying of the heavenly Paradice <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 8, 9, 10 17, &amp; 3, 22, 23</note> given everlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What was the puniſhment of breaking the Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A deprivation of all happineſſe, and <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> eternall death.</p>
            <p>As a Rebell with all his goods.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did man keepe the Covenant which hee made.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, Man brake his Covenant. <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 6. 1 Tim. 2. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came man to breake his Covenant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the temptation of Sathan. <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came Sathan to be a Tempter?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jude 6. 2 Pet. 2. 4. Act. 12. 15. Gen. 3. 15. 16. Heb. 1. 4, 5, 6. Rom. 10. 5, 6. Hab. 2. 6. 7. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He diſliked man ſhould be above him.</p>
            <p>For Angels are ſervants to man in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice eſtate.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came man to be greater then Satan who was an Angell of Light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the covenanted gift, wherein hee had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120063:7"/> Paradice given him.</p>
            <p>For man was not created heire of Paradice, <note place="margin">Pſalm 8, 6, 7, 8. 9. Gal. 4. 23.</note> but Lord of the Earth, and heire of heaven by promiſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came the Fiſhes, Beaſts and Birds to loſe their right?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the fall of their Lord, and helpe they <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 6. 13. Rom. 8. 16.</note> uſed to betray him.</p>
            <p>As when a great man proves a Rebell, all his riches are confiſcated.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What harme was mans having heaven given him, unto the Angels?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 18. 10. Pſal 91. 11. 12. Luke 4: 10. 11</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They were to be ſerviceable to man more then before.</p>
            <p>As he that is ſervant to attend a Family, when more are received, have more worke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore was Sathan caſt out of heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For diſliking this eſtate (this Covenant <note place="margin">Jude 6. Luke 20. 36.</note> God made with man) brought him to.</p>
            <p>For in his creation he could not faile, unleſſe <note place="margin">James 1. 13</note> you make God his Creator to be his overthrow.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What eſtate was man in when he had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Covenant?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4. 5. &amp; 3, 17. 1 Cor. 15. 21. Iſa. 30. 33.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Curſed in his created happineſſe, and in his Covenanted worſhip, and ſubject to death of body, and eternall hell-fire.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What did man in this his curſed condition?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 7, 8, 9, 10. James 2. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Cover his nakedneſſe by his owne inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Flee Gods preſence with a terrible conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of being guilty of all the Commandements. <note place="margin">Nehem. 9. 14. Exod. 20. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:120063:8"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Commandements are there?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 22. 37. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 39, 40. Luke 10. 25. 26. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Ten, wherein is contained the whole Law and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who gave the ten Commandements and wrote them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God gave the tenne Commandements <note place="margin">Exod. 19 20. &amp; 20. 1. &amp; 31. 18.</note> and wrote them with his owne finger.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where did God give the tenne Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements in writing firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> On Mount-Sinah. <note place="margin">Exo. d19. 20. &amp; 31. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what did God write the tenne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In two Tables of ſtone. <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 13. &amp; 9, 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To whom did God deliver the ten writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To <hi>Moſes</hi> for his peculiar people to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. <note place="margin">Pſa. 147. 29, 20 Deut. 4. 7, 8, 34</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Did not God require that all under the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralites juriſdiction ſhould be compelled by them to keepe the ten Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: he would not have them require the <note place="margin">Exo. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 44, 45, 46, 47, 48. Joſh. 16. 10. Levit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. 44. 2 Chr. 8. 7, 8. Jer. 15. 19.</note> Gibbonites, Hittites, Gargaſhites, Hivites, uncleane Iſralites, or any unbeleeving Gentiles that lived in the Land with them, to keepe his Faſts or feaſts, or any of his worſhip that was contained in the firſt Table; For that was abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination unto the Lord.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Commandements did God write in the firſt Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Foure. <note place="margin">Marke 10. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120063:8"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Commandements did God write in the ſecond Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Six. <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore did God write the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements in two Tables of ſtone, and not in one Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To teach us that his Son Jeſus Chriſt at <note place="margin">Math. 5. 38. 2 Cor. 10. 4. Math. 22. 21. Iohn 6. 15. Levit. 19. 19. 1 Cor. 5. 12. Deut. 22. 12.</note> his comming in the Fleſh, ſhould ſeperate his kingdom of the world, and his kingdome of worſhip in government &amp; governours one from the other, not permitting them to be joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as linnen and woollen, nor yet ſown with the mingled ſeede of worldly power and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doe the Commandements of the firſt Table teach us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Whom we muſt worſhip, 2. With <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 2, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Math. 9. 10. Col. 2. 4. 1 Cor. 16. 2:</note> what Ordinances he will be worſhipped, 3. In what order he wil be worſhipped, 4. And what time he will be worſhipped.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What do the Commandements of the ſecond Table teach us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To love our Neighbour as our ſelves, and <note place="margin">Math. 19. 19</note> doe as we would be done unto.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me. <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this Commandement negative or affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Negative, or forbidding. <note place="margin">Math. 4. 10. Iames 4. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the affirmative part of this firſt commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:120063:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt have me only and alone for thy <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 14, 7. ſay 45. 13.</note> God, Law-giver, Commander, and Director.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Exod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this ſecond Commandement negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the affirmative part of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt take onely what God makes <note place="margin">1 John 2: 4. Deut. 5. 32. Rom. 8. 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iohn 15, 10.</note> whereby to worſhip him, and helpe thee in his worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the reſt of this ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. The particulars, what wee muſt not make, 2. The end why we may make nothing, 3. And the reaſons wherfore wee may make nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the particulars we may not make to helpe in worſhip?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 15. 19. Col. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20, 21 Iſa 24. 5. Levit. 17. 7. Rom. 8. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Graven Image, likeneſſe, ſimilitude, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, or order, to helpe in the way of worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Wherefore may we have nothing, but that God makes only, in or about worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God will puniſh thoſe that do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and their Children, and will ſhew mercy <note place="margin">Exod: 20, 5.</note> to them and their children that keepe his truth.</p>
            <p>For if we make any thing to helpe in worſhip <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 1.</note> we thereby deny that which God hath made to be ſufficient.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:120063:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the third Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note> thy God in vaine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this third Commandement negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is negative.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the affirmative part of this third Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt reverence the Name or Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <note place="margin">Acts 4. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 13. Pſalme 119. 133. Iſa. 9, 7. Col. 2. 5.</note> of God in all thy diſcourſe and order of his Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the reſt in this third command?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The reaſon, Becauſe the Lord will not <note place="margin">Exod. 2. 7.</note> hold any guiltleſſe, that uſeth his Name (or Power) in vaine.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat is the affirmative part of this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the third Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They ſhall be guilty of ſin, and liable to <note place="margin">Iſa 42. 4. 5. Gol 2 11. 12, 14. Rev. 2. 2.</note> puniſhment, whoſoever doe uſe the Name (or Power) of God in any other order than he hath appoynted in his Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What condition are they in, who live in the breach of this or other commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are out of the Law of faith, led <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 27. Deut. 28. Tit. 1 15. Iam. 2. 10.</note> by Satan, under Gods curſe in all externall things, both concerning this life, and that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Remember the Sabbath day to keep it <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 8, 9.</note> holy; In it thou ſhalt doe no manner of work:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120063:10"/> Six dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all that thou haſt to doe, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this Commandement negative or affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Both negative and affirmative. <note place="margin">Exo. 20. 9. 10</note>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which is the affirmative part of this fourth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Keep holy the Sabbath; ſix dayes thou <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 9, 10</note> ſhalt worke, doing that thou haſt to doe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the negative part of the fourth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no worke on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 10.</note> day by thy ſelfe, ſervants, or cattell, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhich are the workes may be done on the Sabbath day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All workes of preſervation, (that are of <note place="margin">Iohn 5. 17. Acts 10. 35. &amp; 20. 7.</note> neceſſity) and all works of worſhip, required in the written word.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhy is the word</hi> Remember <hi>prefixed to this fourth Commandement, and to no other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe there is an Inſtitution poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out Sanctification in Chriſt, annexed more <note place="margin">Eze. 20. 12. Col. 2. 17.</note> ſpecially to this Commandement then to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the reſidue of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Time for Gods worſhip: for if a God <note place="margin">1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 4.</note> be acknowledged and worſhipped; there muſt be a time for it: but this or that time, or day, knoweth no man by nature.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:120063:10"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the Antitipe (or ſubſtance)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 16, 17. Matth. 11. 28. 1 Pet 4. 14. Exo. 16 23 &amp; 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 12. Lev. 23. 36. Acts 9. 31. Acts 20. 7. 4-9. Heb. 4. 10. 11. Rev. 14. 13</note> 
               <hi>of the ſhadow, that the ſeven dayes holy reſt figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Reſt in Chriſt, reſt in the Goſpel, Church, reſt on the firſt day of the week, (on which Chriſt finiſhed our redemption) and our everlaſting reſt in the glorious heavens.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVherefore was the command of keeping holy the ſeventh day enjoyned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we ſhould reſt, and all we have from <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 10.</note> worldly labour.</p>
            <p>2. To be witneſſe between God and us, that <note place="margin">Eze. 20. 12.</note> he the Lord ſanctifies us in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>3. To teach us our reſt is in Chriſt, <hi>onely,</hi> and <note place="margin">Col. 2. 17.</note> not in our ſelves,</p>
            <p>4. That there is a reſt for us in heaven, where <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 10, 11.</note> Chriſt is entred, which yet we enjoy not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the ſeventh day the Iewes kept holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The day before the firſt day of the week, <note place="margin">Mat 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn 30. 1. 19</note> which Chriſts Diſciples now keep holy.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How comes the 7. dayes Sabbath alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the firſt day of the week?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt who made it changed it: as hee <note place="margin">Col. 3. 16. Heb. 4. 8, 9. 1 Cor. 16. 3. Rev. 1. 10</note> changed the worſhip, ſo he did the time: and as the ſecond Commandement is in force, though the Ordinance bee changed: ſo is the fourth Commandement, though the time be changed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Could Chriſt alter it? was it not Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:120063:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The 7. dayes Inſtitution was a ſhaddow <note place="margin">R vel. 12. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 5. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſay 43. 19.</note> fulfilled by himſelfe: wherefore he made all new, Ordinances, Order, and Time. Yet all the ten Commandements are of force, as of old, and every tranſgreſſion is a breach of them, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 9.</note> tranſgreſſing Iſraelite to bee puniſhed (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are we bound to keep any day holy, wherein we may not doe worldly worke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, the firſt day of the week. <note place="margin">Acts 20. 7. 1 Cor. 16. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1. For if the 4. Commandement enjoyne not a ſet day for Gods worſhip preciſely, then <note place="margin">Ro. 14. 6-13.</note> no Church, nor perſon can blame any of fin, if they be abſent and at work.</p>
            <p>2. For that Action which breaks no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 47. Ro. 4, 5, 5, 6. 1 Iohn 4. 6.</note> is no ſin; for ſin is the tranſgreſſion of the Law.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is the firſt day of the week to bee kept</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ro. 3. 31. Acts 20 7. 1 Cor. 16 2. Heb, 4. 8 9. Rev. 1. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n 20. 1. 19. Mark 16. 2. Lev. 23. 36. Pſa. 118. 24.</note> 
               <hi>holy in obedience to the fourth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, Becauſe Chriſt commands it to be kept holy; and he that obeyes Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, fulfills the Law.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat if we work on the firſt day of the week worldly worke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Wee break Gods command, deny our <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. Ro. 10. 2.</note> Sanctification to come onely from God, and our ſoules reſt to be onely in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVherefore did Chriſt change the 7. dayes Sabbath unto the firſt day of the week?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To teach us that the vails of darkneſſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120063:11"/> from our hearts, and the light excelling (that <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 7-18 Iſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. 7. Heb. 9. 8. 12 &amp; 10. 20. &amp; 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9 Iſay 30. 26. Heb. 4. 4.-9 Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 7. 3 Cor. 16. 2. Gen. 3. 2, 3. 1 Cor. 15. 14-18.</note> light of the Law) now ſhineth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhen did Chriſt begin to ſanctifie the firſt day of the week?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When he had finiſhed all his worke of our Redemption.</p>
            <p>For as God in the Creation did not ſanctifie the ſeventh day, till he had finiſhed all his worke of Creation: So Chriſt did not ſanctifie the firſt day of the week, till he had-finiſhed all his worke of our Redemption.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhen was all the worke of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion finiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When Chriſt was riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n from the dead. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 14. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhen did Christ riſe from the dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Early in the morning when it was yet <note place="margin">Mat. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 30. 1.</note> darke.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhich is the 5. Commandement: or the firſt Commandement of the ſecond Table?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Honour thy father and mother &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this Commandement negative, or</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 16.</note> 
               <hi>affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Affirmative, or commanding.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is the negative part of this fifth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not diſobey Authority, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <note place="margin">Ro. 13. 3, 3, 4, 5. Exod. 20. 12. Eph. 6. 5.</note> Kings, Magiſtrates, Maſters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What if Authority of Parents, Kings, or Majeſtrates, command that which God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in his word?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:120063:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ought in no wiſe to ſubmit unto it: for <note place="margin">Acts 4. 18, 19, 20. Dan. 3. 16. 17.</note> that is the abuſe and not the uſe of authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is the reſt of this fifth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The promiſe that thou maiſt live long in <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 16.</note> the land wherein God hath given theee a being.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Shall I not live long in the land, if I obey not authority?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, the wicked ſhall not live out halfe <note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 23. Deut. 31. 18, 19, 20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> their dayes; But by diſobedience, rebellion, kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c. thou cutteſt off thine own life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the ſixt Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt doe no murder. <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this Command negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the affirmative part of this ſixt Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt preſerve to thy utmoſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 5 44. Rom. 13. 7.</note> the life it ſelfe, but the very meanes of life of every one, even of thine enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the ſeventh Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not commit adultery. <note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 14. 1 Cor. 6 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this Commandement negative or affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the affirmative part of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Commandement?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 28. Eccl. 13. 14. Gen. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor 3. 20. Pſal. 94. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt live chaſte in thought, word, and deed (from all uncleanneſſe.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the eighth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:120063:12"/>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not ſteale. <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this eighth Commandement negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the affirmative part of this eighth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt honeſtly and juſtly, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 9. 10. 11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 4. 28. 1 Pet. 3. 12.</note> to Gods Word) get and keep every thing thou enjoyeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the ninth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſſe againſt <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 20. Exod. 20.</note> any.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this ninth Commandement negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the affirmative part of this ninth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt always ſpeak truth in every <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 25. Prov. 13. 17. 19</note> thing thou uttereſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the tenth Commandement?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 21. Rom. 7. 7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt not covet, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is this tenth Commandement negative or affirmative?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Negative.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the affirmative part of this tenth Commandemet?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 11 Col. 3. 5. 1 Tim. 6. 10</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. Thou ſhalt be content with thy eſtate and condition wherein the Lord ſets thee. <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15. Mat. 1. 21. Pſal. 40. 7. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How comes the wrath of God (which man hath brought upon himſelfe, by the breach of Gods
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120063:13"/> commands) to be ſatisfied?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 7. 9. Rom. 8. 3. Gen. 3. 15. Iſay 9, 6, 7. Mat. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. 1 Cor. 3. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the ſeed of the woman, (Chriſt Jeſus) breaking the Serpents head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How comes man to be free from this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed estate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Onely by the merits of Jesus Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth Chriſts merits redeem all to that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate they had before the fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: hee redeemes none to that eſtate they <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 23, 24. Heb 4. 2. Iohn 17. 9. Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 21. 8. Luke 1. 35.</note> had before the fall, but for thoſe under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, he hath prepared a better eſtate for them eternall in the heavens.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The only begotten Son of God. <note place="margin">Hebr. 5. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Chriſt Ieſus was made, and therefore not begotten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God made him in his body ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth <note place="margin">Gal. 4, 4. Rom. 9. 6. Iohn 1. 14. 3 Tim. 3. 8. Rom. 1. 3. Luke 1. 35. Math. 1. 18. Acts 13. 33.</note> the woman, for elſe he could not have had our fleſh: But in his ſoule he was begotten of God, otherwiſe he had not been free from ſinne.</p>
            <p>For we being all in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſinned both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How could Chriſt be free from ſin, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fleſh of the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>who was a ſinner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The body cannot be ſinfull, the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Luke, 1 35. Mat. 1. 18, 19, 20.</note> perfect, and Chriſt had his ſoule immediately from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How comes children then to be guilty of eternall death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By their ſinfull ſoule and body they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <note place="margin">Pſalm 51. 5. Epheſ. 2 3.</note>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:120063:13"/> from their Parents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth man beget the ſoule of a child?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He doth. <note place="margin">Gen. 5. 3. Pſalm 51. 5. Iudges 8. 30. Levit. 18. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the ſtrength of the ground cannot make a dead ſticke to grow; So the lively nouriſhing part of a woman cannot make that live that hath not life in it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How then can children be viſibly in the ſtate of grace?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17: 4, 7. 10. 1 Cor. 7. 14. Acts 2 39. &amp; 3. 25. &amp; 7, 8. Rom. 11. 16. Hebr. 7. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. By the right which God in Chriſt is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to impute unto them who have Parents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Covenant.</p>
            <p>As when a man is in Covenant with God all his little ones are in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat hath Chriſt done for us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Laid downe his life for our ſinnes, and <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 3. 9. 19. &amp; 14 9. 1 Cor 15. 3. Iohn 10. 17. 18, Math: 1. 21: Rom. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 24. 28. &amp; 4. 2. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20. &amp; 5. 5. Iohn 19 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> roſe againe to make us righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth not man make or helpe to make his owne ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: Mans ſalvation is wrought only and alone in Chriſts own perſon without his helpe.</p>
            <p>For otherwiſe Chriſt did not wholly purchaſe heaven for us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat uſe is there then of good workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Good workes doe confirme the faith I have in Chriſt to be acceptable. <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 21, 22, 23, 24. Gen. 22. 14. Math. 7. 16. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale confirmes the conditions in a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat are good workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Actions done in obedience to Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 15, 16, 17. Iſay 1. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:120063:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doe not good works bring a reward?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, of confirmation of faith, but not <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames 2. 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t 1. 5. 10. Rom 4. 2. 6, 7. Gal. 6. 14.</note> of purchaſe of faith nor heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q Doth Chriſts merits (in this life) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his elect againe to the eſtate they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; In this life we have but the evidence, <note place="margin">Hebr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 15. 45. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 13. 10. 12. Revel. 21. 4.</note> and in the life to come the Inheritance.</p>
            <p>For there can be no perſecution nor imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction when we enjoy our inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat have the children of God in this life by Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 15. 16. Iohn 16. 13</note> Sanctification, <note n="b" place="margin">Ro. 8. 3. Col. 3. 5.</note> Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <note n="c" place="margin">Lu. 21. 19. 2. Theſ. 1. 4.</note> Patience, <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. Col. 3. 5. Eph. 4 14 Iam. 1. 6, 7</note> Conſtancie, <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 11.</note> Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 1. 4. Iohn 16. 13. Rom. 8. 14.</note> Conſolation &amp; direction to lead us to heaven &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q VVhat is Sanctification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">R. 7. 22. Act 38. 6. Ro. 8. 5, 6.</note> A changing of the mind from delighting in the things of this world, to delight in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What is Mortification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ro. 8. 14 Pet. 4. 1, 3, 3, 4. Col. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.</note> A ſuppreſſing of all evill actions which we have formerly practiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the patience the Lord requires?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ro. 2. 7. 1 Pet. 2. 2 &amp; 3. 17. Lu 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 15. 30. 33. Mat. 5, 30, 31.</note> A quiet and meek endeavouring for well doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is Iuſtification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A having our actions which wee performe warrantable to be acceptable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. By what muſt our actions be warranted acceptable?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:120063:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the inward conſcience and outward <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3 20. Heb. 11. 6. Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14. 23. Iam. 1. 22, 23. Rom. 2. 15. 1 Tim. 1. 19.</note> word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is Conſcience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A created faculty of the ſoul &amp; thoughts witneſſing truth on Gods part, by accuſing or excuſing one another without partiality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When are our actions warranted by the conſcience and word?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">3 Iohn 3. 5. Rom. 14. 23. Col 2. 21, 22, 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When both approve the practice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When is one truely conſtant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When hee ſtodfaſtly practiſes (not fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring perſecution) all that he doth to the end <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 58. Col <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 8. Iames 1. 6, 7.</note> without any wavering.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When is one truly comforted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When hee apprehends Gods favour in <note place="margin">Acts 7. 56 &amp; 5. 41. 1 Cor. 15. 19.</note> Chriſt, and the reward ſhall be given unto him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to be directed truly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To bee led by Gods Spirit, not going of <note place="margin">Matth 16. 21. Iohn 16. 13.</note> our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When is one led by Gods Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When he walketh in the wayes of Gods <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5. 78. Pſal. 119. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 19. 7. 11.</note> Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What benefit have the Lords children more then Satans ſervants, in the things of this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They have them in Gods favour, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <note place="margin">Deut. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 16. Tit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Prov. 21. 4. &amp; 16 4.</note> them to happineſſe; and the ohter in his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to keep them till the judgement.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are all that degenerated in</hi> Adam, <hi>reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 8, Act. 15 8. Mat 34 13. Iohn 3. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> None are reſtored but the faithfull with their ſeed.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:120063:15"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith in Ieſus Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Foundation of our hope, and Evidence <note place="margin">Hebr. 11. 1.</note> of the heavenly Inherita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce which we ſhal enjoy.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the object of Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The love and mercy of God. <note place="margin">Math. 9. 18, 21. Acts 2. 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the love of God unto us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All goodnes in this life, and eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the life to come. <note place="margin">Rom. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. Hebr. 12. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Vpon what Object doth Faith worke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Upon the ſatisfaction which Chriſt hath <note place="margin">Math. 9. 18. 22, 23. Acts 2. 38.</note> made for our eternall happineſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the motives that ſtir up Faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The promiſes of Almighty God. <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 9, 10, 11, 13. Gen. 17 4, 8. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cor, 8. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Acts. 19. 21. 2 Tim. 3. 10. 1 Theſ. 5. 12, 13. Phil. 2. 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wha are the effects that flow from faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Confidence of Gods love, internall holy purpoſes, and externall godly practiſes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the internall purpoſes that flow from faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Reſolving in our hearts to obey whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God requires. <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 17. &amp; 8 6. 2 Cor. 8. 10, 11, 12. Mat. 22. 37. 39 Luke 10, 27. Mat. 4. 10. Rev. 22. 18, 19. Deut. 5 32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the externall purpoſes of faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Good workes, ſpirituall and temporall.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are good externall ſpirituall workes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Worſhipping of God in matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to his direction.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are good workes temporall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Helping our Brethren and others, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience <note place="margin">Iſay 58. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ek. 18. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. 2. 17, 18, 21. Mat, 25. 35, 36. Epheſ. 2. 8.</note> to Chriſts Commandements.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How come men to have ſaving faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is the free gift of God.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:120063:15"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What cauſes God to give him faith?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 9. 15. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. His free mercy in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>At what time doth the Lord give his mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Before we are borne. <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 2. Ro. 9 11, 12, 13. Epheſ. 1. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you God gives mercy before we are borne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By his Word, and the manifeſtation of it <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 4. 10, 11.</note> in time.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>By what meanes doth God manifeſt unto us his mercy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. By his Word and Spirit, Extraordinary, and Ordinary. <note place="margin">Jer. 1. 5, 6. Acts 2. 37.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the extraordinary meanes that God uſeth to call by?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Calling us in our miſery or rudenes by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <note place="margin">Acts 9. 3, 4, 5, 6. 1 Sam. 3. 4. Iob 33 14. 15.</note> in a Field alone, of a Viſion in the night.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ordinary meanes whereby God uſeth to manifeſt unto us that we have faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 15. 16. 24.</note> Afflictions, <note n="b" place="margin">2 King. 22. 10. 19.</note> Reading, <note n="c" place="margin">Lu. 14 13, 14, 15. Iohn 4. 27 29.</note> Conference, <note n="d" place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. 2, 3. 4</note> Prayer, <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 2. 37. and 4. 4.</note> Preaching, <note n="f" place="margin">Iob 33. 14, 15 16, 17. Gen. 24. 63.</note> Meditation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not Converſion tyed onely to the Office of the Miniſtery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 11, 19, 20 21. &amp; 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Cor. 14 24, 25, 29, 30. Iam 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Pet. 2. 2.</note> No, it is not at all tyed to the Office of the Miniſtery, but to the Word and Spirit.</p>
            <p>As Corne hath not its growth from the Seeds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but from it ſelfe and the ground; So Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion hath not its from the Miniſtery, but from the Word and Spirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Have thoſe any right to the things of this life, which are not of Chriſts eternall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:120063:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To all created things they have. <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 14. Deut. 2. 4, 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe God hath given the things of this life unto them.</p>
            <p>As a Traytor hath right to the portion, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him till the Execution.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth not mans fall deprive him of the things of this life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Mans fall deprives him of all the things <note place="margin">Gen 2. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4. 10.</note> of this life; But for Chriſt ſake, God gives them all men againe for a time.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Have the wicked any benefit by Chriſts Redemption?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 45. Deut. 3. 4, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. l. 37. 7, 8. &amp; 79. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 3. Mat. 5. 45. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ov. 9 7, 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, in all externall things of this life, for God will not yet now take them from them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Have the Elect no priviledge (by Chriſt) in the externall things of this life, more then the Reprobate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the Elect have them in Gods favour <note place="margin">Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 28, Tit. 1. 5.</note> to preſerve them to happineſſe, and the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in his wrath to reſerve them till the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth God heare the prayers of men, not in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God heares and grants wicked men their <note place="margin">1 Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 27<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. Mat. 5. 45. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onah 3 5. 10</note> requeſts in the things of this life, many times for their further judgement.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you that there is a God, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a. 19. 1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>created man, and all other things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the Spirit of God, and the Heavens,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120063:16"/> Firmament and orderly courſe every day and night they make. <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 30 &amp; 10. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doth God require of his Redeemed in his word</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 30. Exod. 20 3. Mat. 4. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That they ſhall ſerve him only.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth the Lordrequire that wilfull wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men ſhould ſerve him in his divine worſhip?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 16. Jude 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. 4. 5, Mark. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 3 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: they ought not to meddle with Chriſts divine worſhip.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When is one a wilfull wicked man that profeſſeth Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. When he will take away or adde to any <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 9. Mark 13 9. 14 Rev. 13. 10, &amp; 22. 18. 19.</note> thing in Gods worſhip: impriſon or put to death for not worſhipping God as hee would have them.</p>
            <p>For Chriſts ſervants muſt let wicked men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 29. 30 2 Tim 2 24, 35. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Deut. 32. 46. 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17.</note> quietly,</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the law of Chriſts divine word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The holy Scriptures which are called the Old and New Teſtament,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How know you the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to be Gods word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe Gods glory is therein wholy <note place="margin">Iohn 7. 18. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 23. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames 4 6 &amp; 3. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d. 19. Matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 13. 1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11</note> maintayned, mans pride wholy ſuppreſſed, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature utterly gainſayed, evill forbidden, and vertue required.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you our tranſlated Scripture (which is called the Bible) to be the true word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. 1. <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. 14, 15. Ioh. 16. 13.</note> Inwardly by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:120063:17"/>
            <p>2. Outwardly by the power which the word <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. 37. &amp; 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 2 Cor. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> hath, in converting men, and governing them being converted.</p>
            <p>3. By the agreement of the Word, it being <note place="margin">Cor. 14. 32, 3. 2 Peter 1. 1.</note> written ſo many yeates aſunder, and by ſo many ſeverall prophets, and no one place contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting another, being rightly underſtood.</p>
            <p>For where one place (ſeemingly) contradicts <note place="margin">Mie 25. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Math. 2. 5, 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalm 22. 18. Math. 27. 35. Zach. 9. 9. Math. 21 5, 6. Mar. 15. 15. 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay 5. 6, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dan. 11. 31. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 13. 14. Math. 24. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 4. 3, 4. Tim. 4. 3. Rev. 18. 13. Ezek 13. 19. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn 16. 1, 2. Mat. 23. 34. Rev. 18. 8. 21. 1 Cor. 15. 21, 22. 1 Theſ. 4. 16, 17. Math. 25. 23. 34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Math. 12. 33. Gal. 5, 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pſal. 19 7, 8, 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 3. 16, 17. Tit. 1, 2. Mar. 7. 37. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 1. 31.</note> another, it is not rightly underſtood.</p>
            <p>4. By the Propheſies thereof, which are three fold: paſt, preſent, and to come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>a</hi> Promiſes paſt, which are fulfilled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>b</hi> Promiſes preſent, wee behold with theſe eyes, taking away Gods Ordinances, and placing mens inventions in the roome thereof; forbidding ſound doctrine and Gods people to ſpeake his truth: without their licence marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, meats, ſelling ſoules for money, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>c</hi> Propheſies to come that ſhall be fulfilled: deſtruction of thoſe Soule-Merchants &amp; forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to ſpeake Gods truth, reſurrection of the body, Chriſts comming to judgement, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How know you that yuo have the ſpirit of God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>d</hi> By the fruite of good workes which it brings forth in my converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How know you that the word of God is ſufficient?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>e</hi> Becauſe a perfect God cannot leave an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect word.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:120063:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How can the word be ſufficient, ſeeing many bookes ſpoken by the Prophets, are now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The Lord hath reſerved ſo many as are <note place="margin">Ioh. 20. 30, 31. &amp; 21. 25. 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17.</note> ſufficient to teach all things needfull to ſalvation and worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How muſt our eternall God be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As he hath required in that his word only, <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 Cor. 11. 1, 3. Deut. 18. 20.</note> without adding or detracting in matter or order.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What order muſt Chriſts Church and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren keep, in the performance of his Ordinances?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That order onely which in his word he hath required. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40. Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. 1 Cor. 11. 1, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heb. 8, 5. 3 Cor. 1. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How if any breake the order in worſhip that God hath prefixed in his word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He will deſtroy them, if they repent not. <note place="margin">2 Chron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. 16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. Levit. 10. 1. Act. 6. 14. Col. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. Rev. 2. 16. 5. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 2. 1, 2, 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As a King will deſtroy all thoſe that will take money, contrary to the order he appoynts.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſervice that God in his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word requires of his children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is temporall and ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the temporall obedience the Lord</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 37. 38 39 Mar. 12. 31</note> 
               <hi>requires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To obey Parents, Kings, and Majeſtrates, <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 14. Iam. 2. 8, 9. Rom. 13. 1. Tit. 2. 2 1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 4. 11.</note> in earthly things, pay that wee owe, be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to all, ſober in our carriage, doing as wee would be done unto for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May wee not obey the temporall authority of Parents, Kings and Magiſtrates, in Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:120063:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, we may not, for Kings and Parent, <note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. &amp; 16. 12. Gal. 1. 10 Dan. 3. 16, 17, 18. Pſal. 105. 14, 15. &amp; 149 8, 9. &amp; 2. 10, 11, 12. 2 Cor. 10. 4</note> &amp;c. are ſubject in divine things, and ought not to uſe temporall authority, about matters of worſhip.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the divine worſhip the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of his children?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 6. 6. Dan. 6. 10.</note> It is Perſonall, <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 4. 9, 10 Ioſ. 24. 15.</note> Domeſticall, <note n="c" place="margin">Mar. 9. 38, 39. Acts 18. 24, 25, 26, 27.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregative, <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 2. 1 Cor. 1. 11. Deut. 6. 7. &amp; 11. 19.</note> and Stative or in the Church.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the perſonall worſhip the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of his children?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 6. 6, &amp; 14 23. Rev. 1. 9. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That one conſcionably ſerve him when he is alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the duties which one alone is to performe unto the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 8. 28.</note> Reading, <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 1. 29.</note> meditation on Gods Word, <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 11. 33.</note> Prayer, <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 35. 13. Iohn 5. 39. 3 King. 22. 10, 11. 19. Neh. 13. 12, 13. Mat. 22. 31, 32, 33, &amp; 21 16.</note> Faſting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat benefit is there by reading of Gods word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We are informed what we ſhould do, and either confirmed or confounded, in what we have done, that it is good or evill.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit is there by meditation on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 92. Matt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. Luke 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 30 &amp; 2. 35. &amp; 12. 17. 18. Ex. 32. 10, 11, 14 30, 31, 32. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 5. 14, 15. Act. 4. 31, 33. Ionah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gods word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Keeping the knowledge and comfort wee have and gaining more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat benefit by fervent &amp; faithful prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Preventing deſerved puniſhments, and procuring undeſerved favours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:120063:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A powring out of the meditations of the <note place="margin">Pſal. 142 2.</note> heart unto the Lord, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> opperation of his Spirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat is reading of prayer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for prayer?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iona. 2. 8. Pſa. 119. 113. Zach. 12. 10. Dan. 9. 3, 4. 19. 27. Act 4. 24. Ro. 8. 26, 27. 1 Cor. 14, 15 Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 43. 47. Rev. 1 11. Pſa. 50. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An humane invention of man, never heard of in Gods Word, but hated of him.</p>
            <p>For when we read, God ſpeaks to us: and praying, we ſpeak to God.</p>
            <p>2. If reading be prayer one may carry them in his pocket, or buy a penny-worth at a Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhop.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is holy Faſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Abſtaining from food, for Conſcience ſake. <note place="margin">Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 4. Dan. 10. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit is there by faſting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more then by prayer alone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Prayer and Faſting joyned together, will <note place="margin">Matth. 17. 21. Act. 10. 30,</note> prevaile, when Prayer alone will not be heard.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat are the ſpirituall duties the Lord requires of his ſervants in their houſes?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 10. 1, 2. &amp; 17. 11. 1 Pet. 4. 10. Deut 6. 7. &amp; 11. 19. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov. 22 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Prayer, 2. Reading, 3. Conference, 4. Teaching the Word, 5. and continually convenient talke of the Saints unto them.</p>
            <p>For if the youngling bee ſeaſoned in good things, it will abide for ever.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How if ſome of his houſhold will not pray, nor be inſtructed by him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He muſt patiently let them alone. <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 24, Acts 13. 46, 47 2 Cor. 1. 24. Mat 13. 29, 30 2 Tim. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4, 35</note>
            </p>
            <p>For no man hath power to command in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine things (by temporall authority) the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any in worſhip.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May a father maſter, or any in authority,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120063:19"/> force to divine obedience, by Civill power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They may not: All muſt come to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 4. Heb. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> willingly.</p>
            <p>2. If any practice before faith, their Sacrifice <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. 3. Hebr. 11. 6.</note> is of God hated.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May a Father, Master or King, keep ſuch in his houſe or kingdome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He may lawfully, and muſt, (or elſe he rebelleth againſt God) for if his wife or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 13, 14. Math. 10. 35, 36. 1 Pet. 3. 1.</note> be unbeleeving he muſt keep them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat authority hath a Father, King, or Maſter on thoſe who are wicked in divine things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Manifeſt Gods eternall judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 44. Iude 23. Acts 13. 10, 11. Mat. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5 31.</note> them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How if the threatning Gods eternall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will not cauſe them to amend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They muſt leave them as of God not ye called. <note place="margin">Mat. 13, 28, 29, 30. 2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 24. 1 Cor. 14. 37, 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat muſt converted Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants doe in a houſe when their Governours are not?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Abide faithfull, doing what good they can. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 21. Mat. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, 22 1 Tim. 6. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat worſhip muſt the unconverted houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold performe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> None, for their beſt is hated. <note place="margin">Pſalm 50. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Ought any to be let live that will not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord according to his word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They ought: for Chriſt will have none <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 29, 30.</note>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:120063:19"/> bodily puniſhed, for any divine worſhip they <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 24.</note> performe.</p>
            <p>2. For all bodily weapons are prohibited in <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 4.</note> divine actions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVill not wicked men if they be let alone draw many to falſe worſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, ſuch as themſelves are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Ought not Chriſts ſervants to deſtroy ſuch</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 5. 37, 38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>wicked worſhippers for his cauſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for Chriſt will have his children <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 29, 30. Revel. 13. 10.</note> permit wicked worſhippers quietly.</p>
            <p>2. For they may in time be converted. <note place="margin">Acts 9 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. May not people aſſemble together in the name of Chriſt to doe him worſhip, that are not a Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Yes, they may. <note place="margin">Luke 24. 13, 14, 15, 16. Acts 16. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Can a Congregation, (which is not a Church) met in the name of Chriſt) give and receive the Ordinance of Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No, theſe belong onely to a Church, or to <note place="margin">Deut. 12. 13, 14. &amp; 16. 2. 5, 6. Luke 3. 12. 1 Cor. 11. 26, 27.</note> one extraordinarily called and approved of God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVho are the whole Kingdome or Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. All the inviſible, and viſible Saints of God, in Heaven, on earth now, have ever beene, <note place="margin">Math. 8 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke 14. 233 24.</note> or ever ſhall be.</p>
            <p>For all Saints can make but one body, to one head Chriſt. <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 22,</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:120063:20"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where is this univerſall Church planted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. In the gloriovs heavens, (where Chriſt the head is) whither the elect ſhall aſcend, <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 23. 2 Tim. 4. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are officers to this Catholike Church, or univerſall Kingdome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts; who <note place="margin">Heb. 2 4. Act. 19. 11, 12. 1 Cor. 4. 9.</note> are extraordinary called, and approved of by Chriſt our King, and no other.</p>
            <p>For theſe are to appoynt the worke to other <note place="margin">Act. 6. 3.</note> Officers: As the Kings privy Counſell, are by the Kings appoyntment, to declare to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Officers, what the King would have them doe?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is an Apoſtle?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A peculiar Ambaſſador in Office, ſent with Authority to declare the unwritten mind <note place="margin">Eph. 6, 20, Ioh. 20. 23. Matth. 18. 18. 1 Cor. 12. 29. Luke 6 13. Hct. 2. 42.</note> of Chriſt: whoſe writings are the Doctrines and Lawes of his Church, by which all mens fins are remitted, or retained, and by which all ſhall be judged at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>How can Chriſts Church be ordered now the Apoſtles are abſent and dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are ſpiritually preſent and living. <note place="margin">Luke 16. 29. 1 Cor. 15 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As the Kings Privy Counſell are preſent where their commands are; though they be not there in bodily preſence.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is this univerſall Church or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 4 8. Rev. 1. 11. 1 Cor. 1, 2 Gal. 1. 2. Phil. 2. 19. 20. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ov. 27. 23.</note> 
               <hi>distinguiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Into divers branches, particuler States, Churches, Bodies, Cities, or Corporations.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:120063:20"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is a particular Church ſtative body,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37. 39. Ro. 1. 6, 7. &amp; 10 14, 15. 17. Iohn 15. 19 Acts 4. 1. 4. &amp; 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn 17. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Citie or Corporation of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. A company of people called to beleeve and profeſſe obedience unto God in Jeſus Chriſt, by the power of his word.</p>
            <p>2. <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 17. 4. 7. 9. 11. 2 Cor. 8. 5. Luke 1. 27. Act. 3. 25. Neh 9. 38. &amp; 10. 29. Rom. 11. 27. Gal. 3. 17. Heb. 8. 6. 10. &amp; 13 20.</note> Joyned together in holy Covenant, <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 15. 19. Act. Act. 19. 9. Pſal. 26. 4, 5. Tim. 6. 3. 4, 5, 6. 2 Cor. 6. 7. 1 Cor. 5. 12. Rev. 18. 4. Iſay 52. 11 Ier. 6. 1.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the worlds worſhip and ſervice of Anti-chriſt, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 110. 3. 2 Cor. 9. 13. Iſa. 44. 5. Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. Act. 2. 41. 17. 4.</note> by voluntary profeſſion of the faith of Chriſt in the fellowſhip of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>3. Having his power always among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <note place="margin">Math. 18. 17 20 1 Cor. 5. 4, 5. 2 Cor. 2. 6, 7, 8. 1 Tim. 5. 19, 20.</note> (without the helpe or aſſiſtance of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others) to puniſh vice, and ſupport vertue.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the matter whereof Chriſts Church is made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Viſible holy Saints and no other. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 1, 2. Heb. 1. 3. Ro. 17. 2 Cor. 1. 1. Epheſ. 1. 4. 1 Theſ. 2. 10. Act. 9. 4. 1 Pet. 1 6. 2 Cor. 13. 13. Col. 1. 2. 1 Theſ 5. 27. Heb. 13. 24. Exod. 12. 43. 48. 1 Cor 5. 5. 6, 7. 1 Iohn 2. 19. Acts 8. 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When doth one appear to be viſible matter for Chriſts particular Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When his divine word doth powerfully <note place="margin">Acts 2. 37. 41. Lu. 9. 62. &amp; 3. 7, 8. Mat. 3. 7, 8, 9. Acts 8. 21.</note> provoke him to confeſſe in word and deede, Chriſt to be the Son of God, and only to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed in his worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:120063:21"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that which makes Beleevers to bee a particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A holy covenanting themſelves together <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5. Nehe. 9. 38. Heb. 13. 20. Mat. 1. 18. Lu. 1. 27. Iſa 62. 5</note> to be a Church in the order of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>As a man and a maid become one body in marriage by a Covenant or Contract they make one with the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When have people made a holy Church co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When they together have vowed or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed <note place="margin">Nehem. 9. 38. 2 Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 15. 12, 13, 14. Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s 3. 25.</note> in a bodily or Church eſtate to walke together obediently in all things to Chriſts precepts.</p>
            <p>For a Covenant conſiſts in words. And the <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 2. 10. 1 Chro. 17. 23. Dan. 11. 32.</note> performance in the practice? If it be not ſo, how could any breake Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is that keepes Chriſts faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects (being thus joyned) in holy Church peace together?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 18. 20. Eze. 37. 10. Math. 16. 19. 1 Cor. 5. 4. Heb. 5. 14. 2 Tim. 4. 8. 1 Cor. 5. 4. 12. 2 Cor. 8. 9, 10</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſts word and cencors according thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. When is Chriſts holy Church powre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When they in Chriſts name (without helpe of any others) can caſt out ſinners from them, and receive the regenerate that are not of them. <note place="margin">Math. 18. 20. Heb. 1. 3. 1 Pet. 1. 16. Epheſ. 1. 4. Epheſ. 3. 5. 23. Nehe. 9. 38. 1 Cor. 5. 4, 5. Math. 18, 20.</note> them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q What are the eſſentiall markes of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Holy people, holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovenant, holy power.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:120063:21"/>
            <p>As to the body of a man there muſt be true <note place="margin">Ezek. 37. 3, 4. 5, 6. 11. Eph. 4. 16, Col. 2. 19.</note> bones, true fleſh, and true breath, or elſe no man: So if any of theſe three be wanting, there can be no Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What power hath Christ left to each one of his particular Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All the Church authority which he in this <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 21. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atth. 18. 20. 1 Cor. 5. 12. &amp; 16. 3. 2 Cor. 12. 13.</note> life hath afforded unto the Sons of men.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath not one Church of Chriſt power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: every Church of Chriſt hath power <note place="margin">Revel. 1. 13. 2 Cor. 12. 13.</note> equally and alike.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the power which Chriſt hath left unto his particular Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Spirituall keyes which he hath given to <note place="margin">Matth. 16. 19. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 4. 12. Mat. 18. 18, 19. 20. 1 Cor. 3 21, 22.</note> open and ſhut Heaven, with all his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are thoſe keyes which doe open and ſhut Heaven?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the Spirit of God &amp; the word. <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 26. Act. 2. 4. Rom. 8. 9. 14. 16. 1 Cor. 2. 12. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn 3. 24. &amp; 2. 27. Ioh. 12. 48.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Can none but the Saints open and ſhut Heaven with the key of Gods word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 10. 4. &amp; 7. 22, 2,. &amp; 25. 25.</note> Yea, Reprobates, though damned for their labours.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lu. 10. 17. Mat. 7. 22.</note> As one may open the door that takes the key without authority: For the key of the word will open where faith is.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How comes Excommunication, ſeeing the Spirit of God and the word are thoſe keyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By turning thoſe keyes againſt the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 4. Math. 18. 20. &amp; 16. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:120063:22"/>
            <p>For if the key of the word locke not out the <note place="margin">3. Iohn 9. 10. Ioh. 4. 35. 38.</note> excommunicated, they are falſely dealt againſt, and the Church ought to repent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Are theſe keyes given only to the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Every Saint hath them in particular. <note place="margin">Iohn 4. 29. 30. 39. Mat 16. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the Ornaments wherewith God adornes every particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 13. Iohn 5. 39.</note> Reading. <note n="b" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 17 1 Tim. 2 8.</note> Prayer, <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 26. 31. Ro. 12. 10. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 21. 1 Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. 10.</note> Propheſying, <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 20. 28. Tit. 1. 5. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. 1. 20 &amp; 2. 1. 2 Tim. 4. 2.</note> Officers, <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 2. Act. 4. 34, 35. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. 10.</note> Contribution, <note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 18. 20. Mat. 16. 19. 1 Cor. 5. 4, 5. 11.</note> Cenſors, <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 28. 19. Lu. 22. 19, 20. 1 Cor. 11. 24, 25, 26.</note> Seals, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What Bookes are the Churches of Chriſt to reade and obey?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 2. 5, 6. Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v 30 5, 6, Pſ l 19. 7, 8 9. Ierem. 1. 8. 2 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 16 17. Gal. 3. 15. 1 Tim, 6. 3, 4, 5. 2 Pet. 1. 16. 19, 20, 21. Rev. 18. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The bookes of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only, wherby God hath appointed to make himſelfefe knowne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. May not the bookes called Apocryfall bee read and obeyed in Chriſts Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They may not, <note n="a" place="margin">2 Mack 12. 44, 45. &amp; 14. 41, 42. Eccl. 46. 20 Wiſd. 19. 11.</note> for they have in them er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſdras</hi> 14. 21, 22, 23. &amp; 12. 15. <hi>Iud.</hi> 8. 33. <hi>Iudeth</hi> 10. 9. 12. &amp; 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. &amp; 14. 3, 4. 1 <hi>Mack.</hi> 9. 3. 18. &amp; 2. 1. 10. 1 <hi>Mack.</hi> 1. 6. 4. 8. 9. 16, 2 <hi>Mack.</hi> 1. 13, 14, 15, 16. &amp; 9. 1. 5. 7 9. 28, 29.</note> untruths, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tobit</hi> 12. 12. 13. 15. compared with <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3. 4. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. 3, 4.</note> blaſphemies, <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tobit</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8. &amp; 9. 2, 3. <hi>with</hi> 3. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 8. &amp; 11. 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>with</hi> 2. 9, 10.</note> magicke, and <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith</hi> 9. 2, 3, 4. <hi>compared with Gen.</hi> 49. 5, 6, 7. <hi>Eſt Apoc.</hi> 12. 5. <hi>with Eſt Can.</hi> 6. 3. &amp; <hi>Eſt Apoc.</hi> 15, 9, 10. <hi>with Eſt Can:</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 46. 20 <hi>with Iſay</hi> 57. 2. <hi>and Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7.</note> contradictions to the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:120063:22"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is prophecying?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 26. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 29 Rom. 8. 12, 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 4. 10. 1 Th ſ 5. 20. Num. 11. 26, 27, 28, 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A teaching of the Word of God (in the Church) by Doctrine, Interpretation, Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlon, or Exhortation, by a member that is not in any office of Miniſterie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What bee the offices that belong to every particuler Church of Chriſt?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 7, 8. Act. 6. 3. 1 Tim. 5. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. Teaching, exhorting, diſtributing, ruling mercy ſhewing.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who ought to chuſe and ordaine the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 20. Acts 6. 2, 3. 5. &amp; 14. 23. &amp; 1. 15. 23, 26. 2 Cor. 8. 5. Eze. 33. 2. Num. 8 9, 10 1 Cor. 16. 3. Heb. 5. 4.</note> 
               <hi>of every particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The Members of the Church where they are to adminiſter.</p>
            <p>As every people of a Liberty, Precinct, or Corporation ought to chuſe and ordaine their Conſtable.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How can a Miniſter be made without lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands by one that is a Miniſter?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 13. 3. &amp; 1 26. &amp; 6. 2, 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Num. 8. 10. Rev. 1. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Laying on of hands, belongs to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer Church, (who are all Kings and Prieſts) and not to any other.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Titus had authority to ordain Miniſters?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 6. 3. &amp; 4. 7 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 16. 3. Num. 8. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No otherwiſe than <hi>Paul</hi> had appointed, which was by the choice of the Church, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:120063:23"/> laying on of the Churches hands or Power.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Is every one that is a Miniſter of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church an Officer all the world over?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, hee is a Miniſter onely to the <note place="margin">Acts 20. 28.</note> Church and People that Elected, and Ordained him.</p>
            <p>As a Conſtable and Major, are Officers only in the limit where they were choſen &amp; ordained and being out of the ſame, they have no offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authority,</p>
            <p>Qu. <note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 42. 5. 6. 1 Iohn 4. 6. Luke 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat muſt the people doe for their Miniſter, when they have choſen and ordained him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hear him preach, <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 13. 7. 17.</note> yeeld unto all truthes he brings from the Lord. <note n="c" place="margin">Acts 20. 36.</note> pray with him, <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 4. 15, 16. 1 Cor 9. 7. 14.</note> and manifeſt their loves in furniſhing him with neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat maintenance muſt the Miniſter have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What the people will freely give him, but <note place="margin">Heb. 7. 12. 1 Cor. 9. 13, 14. Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 410. 414. Rom 15. 17. Gal. 6. 6.</note> no Jewiſh and Popiſh Tithes nor Offerings.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How if the people be not able to maintain their Miniſter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He muſt worke and help to maintain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2. 9. 2 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ. 3. 8. 1 Cor 412. Acts. 18. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As a good Shepheard muſt help himſelfe in winter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll his Sheep can ſpare their fleece.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>VVhat muſt the Miniſter doe for the Members who have chooſen him their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:120063:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13 17. Rev. 3. 3. 2 Cor. 11. 27</note> Watch to prevent danger, <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 20. 27. 31.</note> teach them the truthes of the Lord, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 13. 5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 11, 12</note> ſtand againſt the enemy for them, <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 31. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. 10. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. &amp; 4. 11: <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 5.</note> give warning before danger commeth, <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 13. 17. 1 Cor. 16. 3.</note> arme them againſt it, <note n="f" place="margin">Iames 5. 14, 15. Rom. 10. 1. 2 Theſ. 1. 11. g Iohn 10. 11. Phil. 2, 30. 1 Iohn 3. 16.</note> goe to them that are ſick when they ſend, pray for them, and lay down his life for them if need require, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat muſt the Miniſter doe to the ſick that ſend for him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Pray over him, anointing him with oyle <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 14. 19, 20.</note> in the Name of the Lord</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat muſt the ſickneſſe of the member be that doth ſend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. A troubled conſcience. <note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat muſt be the oyntment that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter muſt anoynt the ſick member with?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="a" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 27. Hebr. 1. 9.</note> Gods fauour in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat is Miniſteriall preaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 20. 28. 35 D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut 17 18, 19. Rom 12. 8. 1 Tim 5. 17.</note> A declaring of Gods Word unto his people by vertue of an office.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat is the Rulers office?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 34. Col. 2. 5. 1 Cor 14. 40. 1 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſ. 5. 14. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 1. Levi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 10. 1. Act. 20. 18. 1 Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 13. 9, 10. Acts 114. Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 5. 1 Tim. 3. 15.</note> To govern the people according to the Doctrine truely taught by the Teacher.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>VVhat is Diſcipline?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. The order or manner the Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to performe every Ordinance in his Church by.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:120063:24"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>May we alter the manner in any one of his Ordinances, that the Lord hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If we may, his appoynted Order was in vain. <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 2. 3, &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For the Lord is as jealous now as under the <note place="margin">Lev. 10. 1 Numb. 16. 1 Chro. 15. 13.</note> Law; and hee that then brake Order was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>3. And we ſee Kings doe puniſh men for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king money diſorderly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the Deacons Office?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 8. Acts 6. 1, 2, 3. 4. 35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To receive and diſtribute the Churches Contribution, providing what is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are they muſt lay apart?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 2. Ro. 15. 27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The members of the particuler Church.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How much muſt every one contribute in the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What they can ſpare, ſee needfull, and <note place="margin">2 Cor. 9. 7. 1 Pet. 4. 11.</note> are willing to doe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>For what end muſt the members of a Church lay apart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For the manifeſtation of their faith, the <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 25, 36 Jam 2. 18. 21, 22, 23. 2 Cor. 9. 7. 1 Pet. 4. 11.</note> helpe of their poore brethren, and Churches neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who muſt looke to the poor and ſick that are not able to help themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Church, by their Officers, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 1. &amp; 12, 8. 1 Tim 5. 10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who muſt pay the charge of the poore members?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:120063:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Churches proviſion. <note place="margin">Acts 61. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not the Deacon adminiſter the Seales of the Church by that Office?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 26. 16. 20. Rom. 12. 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He may not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Vhat are the confirming Seales of every</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. 11. 1 Co. 11 G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 17. 7 11. 27. 2 Cor. 1. 22. Ion. 6. 27.</note> 
               <hi>particuler Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An Ordinance of God, that ſeales mercy <note place="margin">Ro. 4. 12. Iohn 3. 33. Mat. 28. 19. 1 Cor, 11. 29. Matth. 3. 11. Acts 2. 38. Gen, 22 14: Numb 16 37. 38. Lev. 10. 1.</note> or judgement on the receiver.</p>
            <p>For God is preſent in mercy or judgement in each one of his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When is the Lord preſent in judgement in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor 11. 29. Acts 8. 13. 23. Gen. 34. 24, 25. Rev. 22. 18</note> When it is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orderly received, either in Church, Miniſtery, Addition, or unfit parties.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Ought we not to repent of that Baptiſme wherein God is preſent in judgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; for it is Gods Ordinance, and the diſorderly performance or additions of men, <note place="margin">Act 8. 13. Tit. 1. 16.</note> makes not a nullity of the Ordinance, but beares this badge, He is a tranſgreſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>As the diſorderly ſetting on the Kings Seale on any writing, makes it not to be no Seale of the Kings, but it remaines the ſame, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is for the diſorderly performance, the Seale is not queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How comes Baptiſme, wherein God is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in judgement, to be in his favour?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:120063:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By our repentance of the diſorder; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <note place="margin">Ezek. 13. 21. 1 Cor. 5. 2 Cor. 2. 8.</note> of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the eſſentiall parts that belongs to Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> True words (in the name of the Father, <note place="margin">Math 28. 19. &amp; 3. 13.</note> Son, and holy Ghoſt) water, and profeſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is profeſſed obedience eſſentiall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Without profeſſed obedience it is mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 36. Ier. 15. 17. Act. 17. 32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore did Chriſt our high Prieſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To manifeſt the cleanſing of us from our <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 31. &amp; 13 8. 1 Cor. 6. 11. Revel. 1. 5.</note> ſinnes by his ſufferings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What do we performe to the Lord in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of water?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We ſignifie and ſeale, that our ſins are by <note place="margin">Ro. 4 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2. 41. Ioh 3 36.</note> Chriſt ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What Seale is Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Seale of Gods promiſe, made to us <note place="margin">Gen. 17 10, 11. Gal. 4. 28 Act 2. 38. 39.</note> and our children.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit have Gods children by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Confirmation of Gods acceptance, and <note place="margin">Exo. 4. 24, 25, 26. Mat. 3. 15.</note> comfort in that they have fulfilled righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth not Baptiſme of water bring the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It doth not: For the holy Ghoſt muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare <note place="margin">Act. 8. 13. 18, 19. 21. 2 Pet. 3. 20, 21, 22. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 1. &amp; 3. 7</note> in them before they partake of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:120063:25"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>When doth the holy Spirit of God appeare in man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When the grace of God (which inrighteth <note place="margin">Gen 17. 7. Gal. 4. 28. Acts 10. 15, 44 Marke 16. 17.</note> to all priviledges in due order) is any way ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted upon them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How then do children come rightly (who have no underſtanding) to the ordinance of Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the righteouſneſſe which God by his <note place="margin">1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 7. 14. Ro. 4. 6. Iam. 2. 23. Act. 3. 25. &amp; 2. 39.</note> grace in Chriſt is pleaſed to impute unto them, that are borne of Parents under the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 9. 8. Gen. 17. 7. Act. 3. 25. Eph. 2. 12, 13.</note> For the Lords Covenant is with the faithfull and their ſeed.</p>
            <p>2 As by the imputation of Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note place="margin">I am. 2. 23. Ro. 8. 1, 2, 3, 4. Tit. 2. 11. &amp; 3. 5.</note> unto us, we have right to all Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in due order; So by Chriſts Righteouſneſſe imputed unto our children, they have right to all Gods ordinances in due order.</p>
            <p>3. For thoſe whom Chriſt our Redeemer bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 13, 14. 15. &amp; 9. 13.</note> with a ſpirituall bleſſing, had right to baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of water.</p>
            <p>Little children therefore (of beleeving parents, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10. 2. 3, 4. Lu. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15, 16.</note> held up in armes) had right to baptiſme of water.</p>
            <p>Becauſe Chriſt our Redeemer bleſſed them <note place="margin">Mar. 10. 13, 14, 15, 16.</note> with a ſpirituall bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What if any deny children of beleevers in a Church eſtate, baptiſme of water?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They make void the promiſe of God <note place="margin">Act. 2. 39. Gen. 17. 7. Mat. 15. 6. Rom 4. 11. Col 2. 11. 12.</note> (made to children of Beleevers) by that their tradition.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:120063:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. May ſuch as deny children baptiſme, be permitted members of a true Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, they ought to be cut off from all <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 14.</note> Chriſts Congregations.</p>
            <p>For as the children of Beleevers have Gods <note place="margin">Mar. 10. 13, 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 49. 32 &amp; 61. 8, 9.</note> promiſe, ſo he requires every Church &amp; ſervant of his to manifeſt they acknowledg it, by giving the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptiſme a token of Chriſts bleſſing on them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. An Ordinance of Chriſt Jeſus appointed <note place="margin">Lu. 22. 18, 19, 20.</note> for his Church,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What are the eſſentiall parts of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Bread, Wine, and profeſſed obedience. <note place="margin">Lu. 22i19. 20. 1 Cor. 11. 28, 29, 30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth the bread ſignifie, with the breaking thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſts body, and the breaking thereof for <note place="margin">Maik 14. 22.</note> our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat doth the wine ſignifie with the powring out thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſts blood, and the ſhedding thereof. <note place="margin">Mark 14. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. How comes profeſſed obedience to bee eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Becauſe without true obedience we eate <note place="margin">1 Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 11. 29. Mat. 26. 21, 24 47, 48, 49.</note> our damnation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if one of the</hi> 3. <hi>(of bread, wine, or obedience) be wanting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not acceptable eating the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 20. 21. 29.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore did the Lord appoint the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120063:26"/> of his Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To manifeſt the price he payed for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 20. Hebr. 9. 12. 14. 1 Cor. 7. 23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What is the price manifested in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The death of Chriſts body and ſhedding <note place="margin">Iohn 19. 34. Hebr. 2. 9.</note> of his blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What doe wee declare in the partaking of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That we have Chriſt in us (before wee <note place="margin">Heb. 8. 11. 2 Cor 13. 5. 1 Cor. 11. 31. Math. 26. 26, 27, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> partake of it) and are ſaved only by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Why do we often receive the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſeeing we are but once baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. To ſeal that we continue faithfull, go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">Ro. 4. 11. 1 Pet, 2. 2. Ro. 12. 5. 1 Cor. 10. 17.</note> in Chriſts ſervice, &amp; hold mutuall Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowſhip with our Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What harme have they (by it) that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lords Supper, before they truly diſcern what it is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Doubtings of minde, terrours of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 23 30. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 22. 12. 13. Iohn 13. 27 Rom. 14. 23.</note> deadneſſe in grace, and damnation to their ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Doth the command of the Magiſtrate that all ſhall come at</hi> Eaſter <hi>(or ſome other time to the Communion) doe good or harme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It doth great harme, for it makes the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 29. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>br. 11. 6.</note> and unprepared, eat to their great dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Is it not the temporal Magiſtrates duty to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120063:27"/> ſee all receive Christs ſupper at ſome times?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. 105. 14, 15, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. 13 10. 3 Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 24. Pſ. 149. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 11. 61 Co<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11. 28, 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 13. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for hee hath nothing to do with the faith of any in divine things.</p>
            <p>2. Neither hath God appointed any to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it, but Beleevers that can examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>3. And the authority commanding that God <note place="margin">Act 419. Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. 3. 18.</note> hath not appointed, controdicts the Almighty, and may not be obeyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What externall power is it that muſt compell to the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Chriſts divine word only, and not earthly <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 4. Heb. 4. 12. Act. 2. 37. 2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 24.</note> power.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>When are people fit to receive the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When they apprehend Chriſt is in them, <note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13. 5. 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. 28. Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13. 27. 1 Cor. 12. 13. Pſalm 110. 3. 2 Cor 9 13.</note> their ſins are pardoned in his ſufferings, and are deſirous and willing to performe the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. May a member of a Church omit parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Christi Supper, being preſent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Hee may lawfully, his conſcience being troubled. <note place="margin">1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. 27. 29</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVil not the leaving members thus at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, breed confuſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. That breeds no confuſion which God hath <note place="margin">1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14. 33.</note> appointed.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>VVhat neceſſity is there, that every Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33. Act. 20. 28. Lu. 22. 29, 30. 1 Preſ. 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12 Heb. 13. 7. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. 25. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ought to bee a member of a particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Very great, becauſe Chriſt commands the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:120063:27"/>
            <p>2. For Chriſts commands, without being a <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 17. 20 1 Cor. 5. 4 12</note> member of a particular Church, cannot be by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny performed.</p>
            <p>3. None can orderly have baptiſme and the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 33. Deut. 12. 13. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 16. 2, 5, 6.</note> Lords Supper, except they be members of a true particular Church.</p>
            <p>4. It is a wofull eſtate to be out of Chriſts <note place="margin">Ecc'eſ. 4. 10.</note> particular Church: for if one fall, he hath not a ſecond to helpe him up.</p>
            <p>5. Chriſt hath allowed no other eſtate for his <note place="margin">Rev. 1. 11. Gal. 1. Cor. 1, &amp;c.</note> children, wherein to continue in this liſe.</p>
            <p>6. If any may live out of a particular Church eſtate, then every one may, and ſo Chriſts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of particular Churches is made vaine, and none need to continue them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What benefit is there by being a member of a particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Right to all Chriſts priviledges therein. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 21, 22. Pſal. 133. 3. &amp; 87. 2. Gal. 6. 12. <hi>Ro.</hi> 15. 1. Mat. 18. 17. 20. 1 Cor. 5. 2 Cor. 7. 10. Ro. 1. 12. Gal. 2. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. Gods love more in that eſtate, then in any other,</p>
            <p>3. Helpe of the Brethren in all ſailings.</p>
            <p>4. Chriſts power of diſcipline in his Church, to recall us from vice, which elſe-where can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be.</p>
            <p>5. Juſtification of the Brethren, our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is holy, and we in Gods favour.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>To what end muſt every one be a member of a particular Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That they may do his will, and manifeſt <note place="margin">Pſalm 40. 7, 8. Heb. 10. 9.</note> that they rebell not in any thing againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:120063:28"/>
            <p>2. To keepe up that which Chriſt hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3. That Chriſts power may bee ſeene in his <note place="margin">Pſalm 40. 10.</note> particular Churches. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 33. 2 The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 6, 7. 11. Pſal. 37. 23 Deut 12 13, 14. &amp; 16. 2. 5, 6. 1 Cor. 11. 33. Heb. 13. 7. Ezek. 33. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>4. That every one may walke in Gods order and not extravagantly.</p>
            <p>5. That they may rightly have the priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of all Chriſts Ordinances, and approbation of his Church in receiving.</p>
            <p>6. That they may be watched over, kept from danger, and do their duty.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat muſt a Beleever doe to be received a member of a particular Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Live unblameably, and make his publique <note place="margin">Luke 9. 62. Pſal. 110. 3. 2 Cor. 9. 13. Acts 241.</note> profeſſion voluntarily, that Chriſt is the Son of God, his Redeemer, and only by him to bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat must the Church of Chriſt doe to one that offers himſelfe to be a member?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Inſtruct him that Chriſt and Anti-chriſt <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24. 22, 23.</note> or Belial cannot both be ſerved by him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the parties duty, being inſtructed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To make his voluntary anſwer to their <note place="margin">Ioſh. 24. 24.</note> inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if his voluntary anſwer be not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to diſcern him a Saint?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Church muſt leave him with refuſall. <note place="margin">Luke 9. 62. &amp; 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What muſt the Church doe to a member that hath committed evill, and is obſtinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Accuſe him of his ſin in the due order of <note place="margin">Math. 18. 17. 20.</note> Chriſts Goſpell.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:120063:28"/>
            <p>For love thinkes no evill before it ſee it. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not the Church examine the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and conſtraine him to accuſe himſelfe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They may not, for love cannot think evil, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 5.</note> before it behold the ſame.</p>
            <p>2. If the Church may by examination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine any to accuſe themſelves: the oath <hi>Exofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> or Inquiſition is no more.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How muſt a member of a Church behave himſelfe towards oxe excommunicated?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Reſpect him as a Heathen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not a member of a Charch joyn with</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 18. 17. 1 Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>one excommunicated in a divine perſonall act, while he ſtands juſtly cenſured?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for hee is not in order of fellowſhip <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 15. 20. 1 Cor 5. 1 Tim. 6. 3. 6.</note> with him, but remains in his ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not one of a true church have perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall communion with one, that lives in viſible ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He may not, but muſt ſeparate (in all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 17. Iſa. 5. 11. 1 Tim 6. 5. Ier. 15. 19. 1 Cor. 5. 11. Mat. 18. 15. 18.</note> from him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not one complaine on an evill wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper (to the civill Magiſtrate) for his evill worſhip, to have him puniſhed for it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. No: for that were to raiſe perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <note place="margin">Acts 19. 37. 40. &amp; 18. 12. 16.</note> him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is perſecution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Troubling honeſt peaceable people about <note place="margin">Dan. 6. 5. 16.</note> matters of the worſhip of their God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not one then joyne with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120063:29"/> of</hi> England, <hi>in their Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: for their beſt Church actions are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy, in Miniſtery, Order, Power, and place. <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 2. &amp; 16. 13. &amp; 20. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1. In Miniſtery, theirs is from the Biſhops, the Biſhops from the Pope, (in <hi>Maſons</hi> book, ſet forth <note place="margin">Act. 6. 3. Ezek. 33. 2. Act. 14. 23. 1 Cor. 16. 3. Act. 1. 23. 26.</note> by authority) and the Pope from Sathan, themſelves affirme in their preaching commonly.</p>
            <p>Whereas Chriſts Miniſter is from the Church he ſerveth in.</p>
            <p>2. In Order, for the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath <note place="margin">Deut 4. 2. 5, 6. 1 Tim. 6. 3. 6. Deut. 5. 32. Rev. 22. 18, 19. &amp; 10. 9, 10. 1 Corin. 11. 2. 1 Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 15. 13.</note> reading for prayer, a falſe Article in their Faith, blaſphemy in the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, in that they acknowledge Arch-Angels when there is but one Arch-Angel Chriſt Jeſus, croſſing, kneeling, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whereas Chriſts Church muſt read only Gods divine word: and according to the ſame directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therein, adminiſter, confeſſe, and performe <note place="margin">Jer. 1. 7, 8. 2. 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17. Gal. 3. 15. Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9. Prov. 30. 5.</note> prayer, not adding to his order in any circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the performance of his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>3. In power, theirs is by a Commiſſaries Court, or earthly authority in the new Church modell. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 4, 5. 2 Cor. 2. 7, 8, 9, 10. Mat. 18. 17. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas Chriſts Church is onely by his owne Eccleſiaſticall or divine power within the ſame.</p>
            <p>4. In place, theirs are holy by their owne making and yet ſtand undemoliſhed.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Lord hath made all places holy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alike, <note place="margin">Math. 24. 2. Acts 17. 30. 1 Tim. 2. 8.</note> and will not have any place left ſtanding that may enſnare his people.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:120063:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. What muſt one brother in Church fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip doe to another brother that falleth into ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Pray to the Almighty for the remiſſion of <note place="margin">1 Iohn 5. 16.</note> his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>2. keepe his ſin ſecret. <note place="margin">Galat. 6. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>3. Watch a time when he is fitteſt to receive <note place="margin">Act. 3. 21. Pſal. 32. c.</note> inſtruction.</p>
            <p>4. Tell him his fault ſecretly, when hee is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 15, 16, 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>5. prove the act evill unto him by GODS Word. <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 1. 7. Epheſ. 6. 17. Pro. 15. 1. 1 Cor. 16. 14. 2 Sam. 12. 1. Rom. 16. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>6. Uſe moderate ſpeeches with love and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to perſwade him from it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If I ſee my brother ſin, may I not tell ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before I have told him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: It is hatefull to the Lord; <hi>Chams</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 22. 25<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pſalm 101. 56</note> practice, and they curſed that do it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that Church which is mingled with all ſorts of people, profane and wicked?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is a Church of confuſion, where the <note place="margin">Rev. 18. 1. 4. 2 Cor. 6. 14. 17, 18. 1 Tim. 6. 4, 5. Acts 19. 9.</note> Lords people may not tarry.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that Church which was never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted or covenanted together to be a church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> An adulterous practiſer, and ſtealer of <note place="margin">Prov 9. 13. 17, 18. &amp; 5. 3, 4. Dan. 11. 22, 23. Ier. 3. 14. Epheſ 5. 23.</note> that ſhee beſtowes upon the people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 16. Neh. 9. 38. &amp; 10. 28.</note> For without a Covenant, many cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a body, neither in divine nor humane things.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If they could, the children of Iſrael need not to have covenanted when they came out of Babell.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:120063:30"/>
            <p n="3">3. Neither a man with a maide to make her <note place="margin">Math. 1. 18. Luke 1. 27.</note> his wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. VVhat is that particular Church that hath not Chriſts power among themſelves, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe of any) to excommunicate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is an Anti-chriſtian Church. <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 9. Mat. 18. 20. 1 Cor. 5. 4. 1 Cor. 1. 18. Rom. 1. 13. Matth. 15. 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For Chriſt will be with that his Church pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where ever his Church is.</p>
            <p>As a King will be with his power of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where his Aſſize is held.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>vvhat is the matter whereof Anti-chriſts Church is made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A company (externally compelled by ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill authority) of viſible, prophane, blinde zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 17. 19. Rev. 13. 16. &amp; 18. 1. Iſay 1. 2.</note> diſſemblers, and ignorant perſons, which condemn in others, what they practice themſelves and any other that wil, if they by threatning and puniſhing can make them ſay and ſweare as they would have them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is none of Gods Elect in</hi> Babel, <hi>or in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Anti-chriſtian Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is; but they are not of that Church neither is it lawfull for them to continue therein. <note place="margin">Revel. 18. 4. 1 Iohn 2. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>vvhat is that makes men to be viſibly on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with an Anti-chriſtaan Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Joyning and ſubmitting together under <note place="margin">Dan. 11. 23. Rom. 6. 16.</note> their commanded orders.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that which makes men contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Antichriſts ſubjects?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The feare of puniſhment, ignorance of the <note place="margin">Revel. 13. 15.</note>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:120063:30"/> truth, and worldly riches gained by that ſervice. <note place="margin">Matth. 23. 34. Revel. 12. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the markes whereby wee may know</hi> Babel, <hi>or an Anti-chriſtian Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By altering of Gods Ordinances or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <note place="margin">Iſay 24. 5. Dan. 11. 31. Matth. 24. 15. Mar. 13. 14. 2 Cor. 10. 4. &amp; 1 24. Mat. 24. 9. Act. 12. 4.</note> and placing of mens inventions in the ſtead thereof, compulſion to divine obedience by civill authority, forcing men againſt their conſciences to ſay as they would have: &amp; impriſoning thoſe that cannot yeeld unto them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the power which Anti-chriſt hath left unto his Churches?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is wicked Articles, and miſchievous <note place="margin">Luke 6. 22. Matth. 23. 15.</note> tale-telling, is appointed for Courts to open and ſhut hell therewith, that Sathan ſervants may be forced in, and they being in ſhall not get out.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are the Lords children ever the worſe for the Anti-chriſtian Churches (or courts) excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, or puniſhment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: they are much the better, for they <note place="margin">Luke 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2, 23 Ioh. 16. 2. Mat. 5. 10, 11. Mark 10. 29. 30.</note> have particular promiſes of Gods favour more then before.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is not one church of Anti-chriſt inferiour to another, and tyed to obey their impoſitions, or the impoſitions of ſome Anti-chriſtian aſſembly of their Divines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are, as appeares by their Lady Whores of Canterbury and Yorke, with the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh pandering Churches, they (and their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian aſſembly of Divines) raigne over.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth not the giving of the Sacrament, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120063:31"/> preaching of the Word make a true Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> No: then one lying in a Gaole among <note place="margin">Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em. 7. 10. 1 Kings 13. 2. Amos 4. 4. 5. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cha 1. &amp; 6. 16. 2. Acts 13. 2, 10. 12.</note> Theeves and Murderers, preaching the Word, and giving the Sacrament, make theſe Theeves a true Church: for the Lord abhorred <hi>Shilo</hi> for the wickedneſſe of the Prieſts: and <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> though they had Gods Ordinances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not the childe of God ſtand a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of one of the Churches of England, or Anti-Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. He may not: becauſe none of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of England were ſet up of Chriſt, neither are any of them governed by him.</p>
            <p>They were not ſet up of Chriſt, neither in Matter, Gathering, Joyning, Miniſtery, Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Acts, nor Order.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ro. 1. 7. 1 Cor. 1, 2. 2. Cor. 1. 1. Epheſ. 1. 4. 1 Theſ. 2. 10. Act. 9. 4. Heb. 1. 3. 1 Pet. 1. 16. 2 Cor. 13. 12. Col. 1. 2. 1 Theſ 5. 27. Heb. 13. 24. 1 Cor. 5. 5. 7. 1 Ioh. 2. 19. Act. 8. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ex. 12. 43. 48.</note> In Matter: they of the Churchs of <hi>England,</hi> were all perſecuting Papiſts at the firſt.</p>
            <p>When at the firſt, Chriſts Church muſt be all viſible holy Saints, and no other.</p>
            <p>2. In Gathering, they of the Churchs of <hi>England</hi> were forced together by an earthly Proclamation.</p>
            <p>When Chriſts people muſt freely come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into a Church, <hi>(onely)</hi> by the preaching of his divine Word.</p>
            <p>3. In Joyning: they of the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 2. 37. 40. &amp; 4. 1. 4. &amp; 16. 14, 15. 34. &amp; 8. 5, 12,</note> run together as rude people, getting chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120063:31"/> without covenanting, or marrying firſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 23 Nehem. 9. 38. Gen. 17. 7. 9, 10, 11. Heb. 13. 20 Act. 3. 25. Heb. 8. 6. 7, 8, 9, 10. Gal. 3. 17. Mat. 18. 20. Neh 10. 29.</note> When Chriſts Church muſt firſt be marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or covenanted together, before they performe Church Ordinances.</p>
            <p>4. In Miniſtery: they of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> preach by vertue of an Ordinance <note place="margin">Act. 6. 3. Eze. 33. 2. Acts 14. 23. 1 Cor. 16. 3. Act. 1. 23. 26.</note> from an Anti-chriſtian Biſhop, and a licence from him, or the Presbyters.</p>
            <p>When Chriſts Miniſters muſt preach by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that calling the Church whereof he is, ſhall give unto him.</p>
            <p>5. In maintenance: the Miniſters of the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 14. 1 Tim. 5. 17, 18. Heb. 7. 12. Phil 4. 10 Ro. 15. 27. Gal. 6. 6. Mat. 10. 9, 10. Lu. 10. 7. &amp; 22. 25.</note> Church of <hi>England</hi> live by Tithes, Gleabs, and Offerings, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When Chriſts Miniſters muſt live by the free gift of the Church whereof they are, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive for their Miniſtery any thing.</p>
            <p>6. In acts: They of the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have a falſe Article in their Faith, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <note place="margin">Ier. 1 7, 8 &amp; 2. 2. 2 Tim. 3. 16, 17. Gal 3. 15. Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9. Prov. 30. 5, 6. Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 4. 2. 5, 6. 1 Tim. 6. 3. 4, 5.</note> in the Adminiſtration of the Sacrament, in that they acknowledge Arch-Angels, when there is but one Arch-Angel, Chriſt Jeſus: and a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Service or Directory-booke to read unto the people.</p>
            <p>When Chriſts Church muſt read <hi>onely</hi> his divine Word, and according to the ſame Word adminiſter, confeſſe, and performe prayer.</p>
            <p>7. In Order: they of the Churches of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2 1. Heb. 8. 5. Deut. 5. 32.</note> have reſpect of Perſons, Croſſing, Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:120063:32"/>
            <p>When Chriſts ſervants may not reſpect the <note place="margin">Rev. 22. 18. 19. 20. &amp; 10. 9, 10. 1 Cor. 11 2. 1 Chr. 15. 13.</note> rich before the poore in the Church, (in reſpect of this worlds goods) neither adde to his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in any circumſtance in the performance of his Ordinances.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In Government:</head>
               <p>Theirs of the Churches of <hi>England</hi> is by the power of a Commiſſaries Court, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther earthly power newly eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>When Chriſts Government is by his owne Power (without the helpe of earthly power) <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5. 4. 12, 13. 2 Cor. 2. 7, 8, 9, 10. Matth. 18. 20.</note> within his owne Church.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not the childe of God lawfully pray with the Miniſters of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in their Churches?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They may not; for they give acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Hag. 2 12, 13. Iſa. 42. 8. Math 23. 9, 10</note> of making Divine Lawes for the order of worſhip to worldly Magiſtrates, and blaſpheme in their prayers, in giving Primate, Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan, Lord, Grace, Reverend Father in God, unto a wicked creature, which attributes and Honour belongs onely to the Lord Jeſus, and his Honour hee will not give unto any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>May not the childe of God heare the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16. 17. Ier. 23. 16. Mat. 15. 8. 14 Iſay 29 13. &amp; 60. 3. Luke. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Word preached in ſome one of the Churches of England, or Anti-chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Hee may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> For a falſe Miniſter
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120063:32"/> is odious unto the Lord, and all his Saints. <note place="margin">39. Iohn 10. 5. 1 Tim. 3. 6. Prov. 19. 27. Prov. 16. 27. Pſal. 50. 16, 17 Iohn 10. 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>2. For they ought not ſo long as they ſo ſtand to take Gods name in their mouthes.</p>
               <p>3. For the Lords ſervants will not follow them who are ſtrange in office towards him.</p>
               <p>4. For my preſence is an incouraging them in their Coraſiticall practiſes.</p>
               <p>For if none would heare, they would not preach.</p>
               <p>5. If I may hear them who are ſtrange in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <note place="margin">Mat. 1. 24, 25. 34. &amp; 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 12, Luk. 8. 28, 29.</note> to Chriſt, I may heare the Pope or divell, if hee as Satan will preach Gods Word unto me. Yet Chriſt would not permit Satan to ſay, he was the Son of God.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How can it be unlawfull to heare ſome of the Miniſters of the Church of England, (of the old ſtampe, or new forme) ſeeing they are very good men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is impoſſible for any man to be a good <note place="margin">Mat. 23 Num. 16. 1 King. 18. 19, &amp; 22. 24.</note> man, holding a wicked office, (more then for a thiefe to be an honeſt man continuing ſtealing) their goodneſſe is but colour, it is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (as proves) if you touch their Honour, or Riches that ſhould maintaine the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How can ſo many men of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, (being new ſealed with the old ſtamp) be deceived?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> There were 450. falſe Prophets in King <note place="margin">1 King. 13 19: &amp; 22. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, and very few true to ſtand againſt them, (and there are farre more learned Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120063:33"/> ſtamped with the Prieſthood then of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 1. Iohn 4. 1. 2 Tim. 4. 3.</note> and as there were falſe Prophets that did deceive, ſo there are and ſhall be.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How can it bee unlawfull, to be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, pray, or heare Gods Word taught in the Churches of England, ſeeing Converſion is in them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Converſion is not in any of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 26.</note> of England, otherwiſe then the Word of God is among them; which Word converts or condemnes alwayes in all places, and from the Word I acknowledge none may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 3, 4, 5, 6 Rom. 16. 17. Ierem. 15. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But from the Prieſts and people where the Word of God is taught, and had with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Ceremonies of mens Inventions, which they will not amend; all that will have aſſurance <note place="margin">Math 7. 22, 23 Mat. 5. 19, 20, 21, 22.</note> they are the Lords Children, muſt depart, and there may not abide.</p>
               <p>Becauſe ſuch Prieſts and People ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing, are rejected of the Lord.</p>
               <p>2. For their doings and themſelves in divine <note place="margin">Pſalm 101. 3. Prov. 29. 27.</note> worſhip is abhominable unto the Lord and all his Saints.</p>
               <p>3. Such people make a worſhip to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>4 If it bee not ſo, we need not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Congregated worſhip in <hi>Rome,</hi> but doe wickedly in ſtanding againſt them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Where were you Converted, ſeeing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120063:33"/> you were not converted in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In Jeruſalem from above, which is the <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l 4: 16, 27. Pſal. 87. 5, 6. Eſay 54. 1.</note> mother of all Gods Elect,</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is Ieruſalem from above?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is Chriſt and his Goſpell. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How know you Ieruſalem from above to be Chriſt and his Goſpell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe God the Father preached it. <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſeed of the woman ſhall break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gallat. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>head: and there ſhall be enmity betweene the womans ſeed, and the Serpents.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in him all Nations ſhall be bleſſed.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 1. 21. Acts 4. 12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And hee ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There being no other name under heaven gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>EZEKIEL 33. 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sonne of man, ſpeak to the children of thy people, and ſay unto them, When I bring the Sword upon a land; if the people of the land take a man of their coaſts, and ſet him for their watch-man,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If when he ſeeth the ſword come upon the land, he blow the Trumpet and warne the people,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then whoſoever heareth the ſound of the trumpet, and taketh not warning, if the ſword come and take him away, his bloud ſhall be upon his ownn head.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:120063:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee heard the ſound of the Trumpet, and tooke not warning, his bloud ſhall bee upon him: but he that taketh warning, ſhall deliver his ſoule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if the watch-man ſee the ſword come, and blow not the Trumpet, and the people be not warned: if the ſword come and take any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from among them, he is taken away in his iniquity: but his bloud will I require at the watch-mans hands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="creed">
            <pb facs="tcp:120063:34"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS BELIEFE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Beleeve in one Almighty</hi> GOD, <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1. 1. Prov. 16. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Creator and maker of all things,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>diſtinguiſhed in three, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt:</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 10. 30. 1 Iohn 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>but not divided,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 1. 2. Ioh. 1. 1, 2, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>al wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king together in the Creation,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ro. 3. 24. Eph. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Redemption,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 97. 10. Phil. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>preſervation,</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Tit. 2. 11. Ioh. 11. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and ſalvation of Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sonne our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <note n="h" place="margin">Col. 2. 9. Mat. 1. 23.</note> GOD <note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 5. Act. 2. 23. Heb. 7, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and Man;</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Iohn 4. 9. Iohn 3. 17.</note> 
               <hi>begotten and ſent by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſay 7. 14. Lu. 2. 7.</note> 
               <hi>conceived and borne of the Virgin</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; <note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 11 48. Ioh. 19. 12. 15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſuffered under the Roman power,</hi> Pilat <hi>being Iudge;</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 27. 35.</note> 
               <hi>crucified,</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 19. 23.</note> 
               <hi>dead,</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 23. 43. 46.</note> 
               <hi>and his ſoule immediately received by</hi> God <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iohn 19 41, 42.</note> 
               <hi>and his body buried;</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 4.</note> 
               <hi>roſe againe the third day according to the Scriptures;</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:120063:35"/>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Act. 1. 9, 10, 11. Ioh. 20. 17.</note> 
               <hi>and aſcended into heaven;</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 1. 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſits at the right hand of</hi> God; <note n="u" place="margin">Acts 3. 21.</note> 
               <hi>whom the heavens muſt containe for a time;</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 12. Ioh. 1. 29.</note> 
               <hi>in whom all our ſinnes are forgiven;</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4. 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and from thence he ſhall come to judge the living and the dead;</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Matth. 25. 32.</note> 
               <hi>before whom every one ſhall appear;</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Math. 12. 36.</note> 
               <hi>to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 6. 5. 1 Cor. 3. 20. Eccl. 12. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of every evill thought,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 12. 36.</note> 
               <hi>idle word,</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Exo. 20. 7. Mat. 5. 34 35, 36, 37. Jam. 1 26.</note> 
               <hi>vaine oath, and</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rev. 22. 12. Matth. 25. 41. 45, 46</note> 
               <hi>wicked action.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I beleeve in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 14. 26. Ioh 15. 26. Ioh. 16. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſent by the Father and the Son to teach and lead</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Col. 3. 12. 1 Pet. 1. 2. Rom. 9. 11.</note> 
               <hi>his Elect in all truth,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 17. 6, 7. Gal. 3. 9. 11 Ier. 31. 1. 8. Act. 2. 39. Gal. 4. 28. Iſay 49. 22. &amp; 59. 21. &amp; 61. 9. Pſalm 147. 19, 20. Zach. 8. 5.</note> 
               <hi>promiſing the faithfull and their children that he will be their God, &amp; they ſhall be his people;</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 18. 17, 18, 19, 20. Rev. 1. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gal. 1. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Inſtituting by his Apoſtles for them, particular Churches here on earth, and no other;</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 21, 22, 23. Pſalm 1. 49 7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>every Ordinance of God belonging to every one of them;</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>all of equall authority, no one being greater or leſſer then other, either in power or priviledges;</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iohn 15. 10. 14. Iohn 5. 39.</note> 
               <hi>who muſt ſerve him as hee hath commanded in his holy Scriptures,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rev. 22. 18. Deut. 5. 32. Matth. 28. 20.</note> 
               <hi>both in Ordinances,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Colloſ. 2. 5. 1 Cor. 14. 40. 1 Cor. 15. 2. Levit. 10. 1, 2. 1 Chron. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9. 11. 1 Chron. 15. 13. Numb. 15. 16.</note> 
               <hi>and Order,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 13, 14. Mat. 9. 22. Mark 16. 16. Heb. 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120063:35"/> their own faith;</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 19. 1 Iohn 3 20.</note> 
               <hi>with a pure conſcience;</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Hebr. 10. 25. Mat. 18. 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>all Beleevers being bound in duty to have and hold communion in ſome one of them,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 4. 9, 10. &amp; 11. 19. Iſay 28. 10. Joel 2. 3. Deut. 6, 6, 7. 1 Tim. 3. 4. 12. Tit. 1. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and teach unto their children what the Lord hath done for them, and what he doth require of them,</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Acts 6. 2, 3. 5. Act. 14. 23. Acts 1. 15. 23. 26. Ezek. 33. 2. Numb. 8. 10.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; that every Church hath power from God to elect and ordaine their owne Officers,</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 7, 8. 3 Ioh. 10.</note> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in Beleevers,</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 18. 17, 18, 19, 20. 1 Cor. 5. 12, 13. Acts 11. 2. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and excomm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nicate any one of them that lives in tranſgreſſion, without the helpe or aſſiſtance of any;</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 2. 11. Deut. 1. 17. Jam. 2. 9. Acts 11. 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>no one member being more free then another.</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Rem. 13. 2, 3. 4, 5. Exod. 20. 12. Epheſ. 6. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I beleeve that I am bound in conſcience to God, to honour and obey the higher Powers, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and every Officer under him, whether they be Chriſtians, irreligi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, Idolaters or Heathens. The Commandement requires o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to every one of them of what Religion ſoever they be, equally and alike.</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">1 Cor. 15. Matth. 25. 24.</note> 
               <hi>And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the bodies of the Iuſt ſhall riſe to life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iſay 30. 33. Matth. 25. 41. 46.</note> 
               <hi>and the wicked to everlaſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Teach a Childe in the trade of his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 6.</note> way, and when he is old, he ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from it.</p>
            <p>Try all things, keep that which <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 21.</note> is good.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:120063:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 17, 11. Theſe were alſo more noble men then they which were of Theſſalonica which received the Word with all readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and ſearched the Scriptures dayly, whether theſe things were ſo.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 22. To obey is better then ſacrifice, and to hearken, then the fat of Rams.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_notice">
            <p>By me JOHN TURNER, Priſoner of our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> (committed by the Biſhops) neer 14. years, for affirming <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath left in his written Word ſufficient direction to order his Church and children in his worſhip: So that nothing may be done, over not above, nor beſides, what is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein by a Precept and example, or a true gathered conſequence, which I dare not but affirm, though I dye for the ſame. And now delivered, (as abuſively impriſoned all this time) by the moſt Honourable Lords in Parliament, 1641.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 57.</bibl>
               <p>Thankes bee unto God which hath hath given us victory, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Reprinted, enlarged, and rectified by the AUTHOR, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:120063:36"/>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Service-Booke be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ad and obeyed in the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; the Service-Booke may not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe <note place="margin">Mark. 8. 15. Iſay 29. 13. Math. 15. 8. 9. Amos 6, 5, 13, 14. Jer. 44. 16.</note> it is invented by man, contrary to the commandements of God, and beſides, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illed with errours, untruths, and blaſphemies, yea, and contradictions to his word.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Invented by man, in that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ocation <note place="margin">Iſay 66. 3. Rev. 22. 19: 20.</note> of Biſhops and Prieſts, or Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en made it, contrary to theſe Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Errours, in that they pray for the very damned, in theſe words: <hi>All that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vell by land or by water,</hi> when they have <note place="margin">Joh. 17. 9. 19. 20 Rom. 9. 27. 1 Joh. 5. 16.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rayed for Gods Children before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rarie to</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Untruths, in that it holdeth forth, that the Prieſts or Miniſters have power to <note place="margin">Mar. 2. 7. 8. 9.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>give ſins in their <hi>Viſitation of the ſicke,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrary to</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Blaſphemy, in that it acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Jud. 9. Jam. 4. 12. Mat. 23. 9, 10, 11. Luk, 22, 25.</note> Arch-angels, and doth attribute the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les of Primate, Lord, Grace, and Reverend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather in God, to wicked and ungodly men, contrary to</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:120063:37"/>
            <p>Fifthly, Contradictions to Gods word, in <note place="margin">Rev. 13. 17. &amp; 149, 10, &amp; 15. 2 Col. 2. 20, 21, 22, 23. Gal. 2. 4, 5, &amp; 1, 10. Act. 17. 30. 1 Tim. 2. 8. Rev. 22. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſay 55, 1, 2.</note> that it addeth the Croſſe to Baptiſme, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the Lords Supper, holineſſe to their Church high-places, and purſe-penalties for their offendors, contrary to</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May not the Directory-Booke be read and obeyed in the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Directory-Booke may not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt hath made a better, wiſer, more antient, and more infallible booke of directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15. Rev. 22. 18. 19 Joh. 12. 48. Deut. 5. 32.</note> for to direct his Church in his written word then that is, by which all ſhall be judged at the laſt day.</p>
            <p>1. And they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> bring not the firſt and beſt <note place="margin">Deut. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mal. 1. 1 Cor. 12. 13.</note> to the ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fice of God, are accurſed.</p>
            <p>2. There is no word of God to warrant the making of that Directory-Booke, more then <hi>Jeroboham</hi> had for the making of Calves of <note place="margin">1 King. 12.</note> Gold, which he ſet up in two high places; one at <hi>Dan,</hi> the other at <hi>Bethel,</hi> to the confuſion of himſelfe, and his poſterity.</p>
            <p>2. This Directory-Booke is newly inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by men and hath Errour. Untruth, and Contradictions to the Canonicall Scriptures; yea, many directions in it that hath no word of Gods truth to hold forth the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:120063:37"/>
            <p>Firſt, Newly invented by men, in that the <note place="margin">Exod. 2. 4. Rom. 1. 30. Amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſal, 99. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 106, 29, 39. Rev. 22. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Aſſembly of Presbyterian Divines (as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all themſelves) made it 1644, contrary to theſe Scriptures,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Errours, in that by Baptiſme of <note place="margin">Nehe. 9. 29. 2 Cor. 8. 5. Mat. 18. 20.</note> water they make members of their Churches, contrary to</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Untruths, in that by receiving the <note place="margin">1 Cor, 11. 26. 30. 2 Cor. 13. 5. Heb. 8. 10. 11.</note> Bread and VVine (in the ordinance of the Lords Supper) they ſay, <hi>They receive Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> contrary to</p>
            <p>VVhen the exceptable receivers have <note place="margin">1 Cor, 11. 29. Heb. 11. 6. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 11.</note> Chriſt before; and thoſe that have not, receive their owne dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Contradictions to the Canonicall Scriptures, in that they adde a Directory-Booke to Chriſts Booke, of direction in <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 32. Rev. 22. 18. 19 Eze. 43. 8. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k. 22. 19. Mat. 26. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 27 1 Joh. 3. 9. &amp; 5 16. Mat. 13. 31. 32</note> Church worſhip; enjoyne all of every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh (by earthly power) to come to their Aſſemblies: command their Miniſters in prayer, to acknowledge, they are worthy of the heavieſt judgement inflicted upon the moſt rebellious ſinners, <hi>pag.</hi> 9. contrary to</p>
            <p>VVhen Chriſt will have none forced (by earthly power) to come to his Churches;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120063:38"/> neither can his Children be culpable' of tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. 3. Mat. 13. 25. 30 1 Joh. 5. 16. &amp; 3 6, 9. Iude.</note> heavie judgement, of being guiltie of ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which the moſt rebellious ſinners are; and the divell ſinnes no deeper, nor hath more judgement on him; then that of the moſt rebellious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which is unpardonable, paſt all repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and all prayer.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="mock_colophon">
            <p>Printed for the publike good of thoſe that deſire to know the truth, and that deſire the Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhould raign alone Lord, Law-giver, and King in his Church.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
